the guy get to deliver speeches, they don't know what.
那家伙要发表演讲 他们不知道什么
So they use this water and they drink more,
所以他们使用这水然后喝更多
they go on drinking, so they tend to do it.
他们继续喝水 所以他们倾向于这么做
Okay, all right.
好的 好的
Well, welcome, I'm Jennifer Williams from the Department of English here at Calvin.
欢迎 我是来自卡尔文学院英语系的詹妮弗·威廉姆斯
Woo, woo, woo!
哇哦 哇哦 哇哦！
And on behalf of the Center for Christian Scholarship, the Office of Multicultural Affairs,
代表基督教学术中心、多元文化事务办公室、
the Office of the Provost,
教务长办公室、
the Department of Communication Arts and Sciences,
传播艺术与科学系
Department of English, the Department of Philosophy, the Department of Art History, and the Metanexis
英语系、哲学系、艺术史系以及Metanexis
Institute's Local Societies Initiative, welcome to Calvary College and the lecture by Slavoj Zizek.
学院的本地社会倡议 欢迎来到卡尔瓦里学院以及斯拉沃热·齐泽克的讲座
A couple of brief announcements first, there is an overflow room if you don't want to sit on the floor.
首先有几个简短的公告 如果你不想坐在地板上 有一个候补室
It's over in the Seminary Chapel and there's some kind of closed circuit thing so that You can still hear and experience the whole lecture, but you're welcome to continue to be a fire hazard if you like.
它在神学院教堂 有一种闭路电视系统 所以你仍然可以听到并体验整个讲座 但如果你喜欢 你可以继续成为一个火灾隐患
It is a full room, so if there are any empty seats in the middle, if you could consolidate so that those empty seats are now on the outside, that would be nice.
房间很满 所以如果中间有任何空位 希望你们能挤一挤 让这些位置在外侧空出来 那会很好
Tonight's lecture is being recorded.
今晚的讲座正在录制
If you're interested in finding out how to get a copy of that, please make sure you put your name down on.
如果你有兴趣知道如何获得那份录音 请确保你登记你的名字
We have a pad of paper that says recording signs up.
我们有一个记录登记的纸板
there's one in both of these main doors.
这里有一个在这两个主门口
So please make sure you put your name and information down.
所以请确保你登记你的名字和信息
And then finally, we were just curious to know who you all are.
最后 我们只是想知道你们都是谁
So rather than have us all go around the room and introduce ourselves, there are sort of sign-up books at both sides.
所以 与其我们大家都在房间里轮流自我介绍 在两边有一些登记册
And again, we would just love to have your signature just as a record of you being here.
再次 我们很乐意有你的签名 作为你来这里的登记
My first encounter with Zizek's work occurred back in grad school, where I suppose all these things begin.
我第一次遇到齐泽克的作品是在研究生学习期间 我想所有这些事情都是从那里开始的
I was trying to use Kierkegaard as a theoretical model for an argument about modernism that I was trying to make in my dissertation.
我试图使用克尔凯郭尔作为一个理论模型 在我的论文中试图提出的有关现代主义的论点
And one of my advisors was just absolutely adamant that such a thing could not be done.
我的一位顾问坚决认为这样做是不可能的
And she said that to have a dissertation with Kierkegaard, Gertrude Stein, and Conrad would just be weird.
她说 有克尔凯郭尔、格特鲁德·斯坦和康拉德的论文会很奇怪
And as you can tell, I'm scarred for life.
正如你可以看到 我这辈子都有阴影了
So I spent many days poring over books and articles and all kinds of things to see if I could find that perfect quote that would allow me to link all these things together.
所以我花了很多天翻阅书籍和文章以及各种东西 看看我是否能找到那个完美的引用 让我能将这些东西联系起来
And one night, a friend of mine from grad school, Jim, emailed me.
有一天晚上 我的一个研究生时期的朋友吉姆给我发了一封电子邮件
He had found a page from the ticklish subject
他找到了一本《痒点主题》的一页 并且在电子邮件中完整地打了出来
To my delight, there enough, on page 211,
令我高兴的是 果然 在第211页
Zizek makes the connection between Kierkegaard and Monardini that I was miss-seeking.
齐泽克建立了我一直在寻找的克尔凯郭尔和莫纳迪尼之间的联系
So I wrote back to Jim, this is great.
所以我回复吉姆 这太好了
This is great, but what does it mean?
这太好了 但这是什么意思
What does Zizek mean?
齐泽克是什么意思
To which Jim replied, and he'll excuse me, Who the hell knows?
吉姆回复说 谁他妈知道
But if Zizek is writing about Kierkegaard, then you know it's important and you can do it too.
但如果齐泽克在写克尔凯郭尔 那你就知道这很重要 你也可以做到
And this is the same friend, I should say, who was given a t-shirt by his then girlfriend, now wife.
还是这个朋友 他当时的女友——现在的妻子——给了他一件T恤
And the t-shirt had the initials WWZS.
T恤上有字母WWZS（译注：“What Would Zizek Say” 意思是“齐泽克会说什么” 人们用它来讨论问题或情况 试图想象齐泽克可能会如何评论或解释 ）
What would Zizek say?
齐泽克会说什么
And Jim told me later he almost proposed to her right on the spot right there.
吉姆后来告诉我 他差点就在那里当场求婚了
Much have been said, of course, about Zizek's use of pop cultural references alongside these sort of major philosophical works.
当然 关于齐泽克在这些主要哲学著作中引用流行文化的做法 人们已经说了很多
But I find that that's something that really is delightful about his work.
但我发现这正是他的作品中令人愉快的一点
And one of my favorite features of The Fragile Absolute is that I can think of no other work in which Keanu Reeves and Hegel share the same page in an index.
我最喜欢的《脆弱的绝对》特点之一是 我想不出有其他哪部作品能让基努·里维斯和黑格尔在索引中出现在同一页上
But most importantly for me in my work is Zizek's engagement with Christianity in the Christian tradition.
但对我来说 在我的作品中最重要的是齐泽克与基督教传统中的基督教的接触
Zizek's claim about the radical ethical and political capabilities of what some have declared to be the most foundational and universalist of all foundational and universalist traditions, Christianity, are very invigorating.
齐泽克关于基督教的激进伦理和政治能力的主张非常令人振奋 一些人宣称基督教是所有基础和普遍主义传统中最基本和普遍主义的
In grad school, it was my experience that nobody talked about Christianity unless, of course, you wanted to critique it.
在研究生学习期间 我的经历是 除非你想批评基督教 否则没人讨论基督教
And even when philosophers like Jacques Derrida or Alain Badiou would talk about Christianity, it was because they were making religious turns in their old age, as opposed to seriously interrogating the work.
即使像雅克·德里达或阿兰·巴迪欧这样的哲学家讨论基督教 那也是因为他们在晚年做了宗教转向 而不是认真审视这个工作
But not Zizek.
但齐泽克不是这样
And all of this from an avowed atheist to boot.
所有这一切来自一个公开的无神论者
Just to conclude, Stanley Fish recently reviewed Wendy Brown's book Regulating Aversion, Tolerance in the Age of Identity and Empire for the Chronicle of Higher Education.
最后 斯坦利·菲什最近为《高等教育纪事报》评论了温迪·布朗的著作《身份与帝国时代的厌恶、宽容》
And in that review, Fish concludes by stating, Brown's account of how liberal tolerance, and therefore liberalism works is nuanced embracing.
在那篇评论中 费什最后说 布朗对自由宽容以及因此自由主义的运作方式的描述是细腻而包容的
The fact that her analysis does not, and in my view, could not deliver a program for improving the world,
事实上 她的分析并没有 而且在我看来 无法提出一个改善世界的计划
or even a set of reasons for rejecting liberal tolerance makes it no different from any other effort, always doomed,
甚至无法提出一系列拒绝自由宽容的理由 这使得它与任何其他努力没有什么不同 总是注定要失败
to derive a politics from the discourses of postmodernism, anti-essentialism, anti-foundationalism.
从政治中衍生出一种政治 后现代主义、反本质主义、反基础主义的话语
The title of tonight's lecture, Why Only an Atheist Can Believe, Politics Between Fear and Trembling, leads me to think Zizek may have something to say about such claims.
今晚演讲的标题“为什么只有无神论者才能相信 恐惧与颤抖之间的政治”让我认为齐泽克可能对这些主张有话要说
So without further delay, please join me in welcoming Slavo Zizek.
所以 别再延迟 请加入我 欢迎斯拉沃·齐泽克
Thank you very much.
非常感谢
I'm really glad to be here.
我很高兴来到这里
Thank you very much for this nice, maybe too nice introduction.
非常感谢这么好 也许过于好的介绍
What I mean is the following.
我的意思是 当我听到如此温柔美好的话语时 我总是会看看我的身后 你所说的那个真正的我是谁
It's too much for me to recognize myself in it.
我发现自己很难在其中认出自己
And now comes the evil point that the name of this gap between what I experience as my immediate self-identity and the symbolic identity that
现在邪恶的一点来了 我所经历的直接的自我认同和构成我的公众形象的象征身份之间的这种差距的名称
constitutes my public image, that X that you are describing, the name of this gap in psychonetic theory is symbolic castration.
你所描述的X 在心理论理论中这种差距的名称是象征性阉割
So thanks very much for a castrating experience.
所以非常感谢这一次阉割经验
Good beginning, okay.
好的开始 好的
But let's go on in a little bit more serious way.
但让我们以更严肃的方式继续
I hope you will not be bored, the beginning is a little bit more difficult than maybe things happen.
我希望你不会感到无聊 开头可能比较难一些
Okay.
好的
I would like to begin with something probably known to most of you, maybe all of you,
我想从大多数人可能都知道的东西开始 可能你们所有人都知道
two Hollywood productions released to mark the fifth anniversary of the September 11th.
两部好莱坞制作的电影 为了纪念九一一事件五周年而发布
Paul Greengrass's United 93 and Oliver Stone's World Trade Center.
保罗·格林格拉斯的《联航93》和奥利弗·斯通的《世界贸易中心》
The first thing that strikes the eye is that both films try to be as anti-Hollywood as possible.
首先显眼的是 这两部电影都尽可能地反好莱坞
They both focus on the courage of ordinary people with no glamorous stars, no special effects, no grandiloquent heroic
它们都聚焦于普通人的勇气 没有耀眼的明星 没有特效 没有夸张的英雄姿态 只是对普通人在非凡环境下的简洁现实描绘
It is, however, this very touch of authenticity which raises, I think, some disturbing questions.
然而 正是这种真实性的触感 我认为 提出了一些令人不安的问题
The first thing one cannot but note is how both films tell the story of an exception.
首先不得不注意到的是 这两部电影都讲述了一个例外的故事
United 93 is about the only one of the four kidnapped planes in which the terrorists failed, which did not hit its destination.
《联航93》讲述了四架被劫持飞机中唯一一架恐怖分子失败的 没有撞击目的地的飞机
World Trade Center tells the story of the two of those 20 or so policemen, firemen, who were saved from the ruins of World Trade Center.
《世界贸易中心》讲述了大约20名警察、消防员中被从世界贸易中心废墟中救出的两名的故事
The disaster is thus turned into a kind of triumph, most notably in United 93.
因此 灾难在某种程度上被转变成了胜利 尤其是在《联航93》中
Here, a comparison with Spielberg's Schindler's List is instructive.
在这里 与斯皮尔伯格的《辛德勒的名单》比较是有启发性的
Although I think Schindler's List is a failure, the idea to choose Schindler as a hero was a correct one.
尽管我认为《辛德勒的名单》是失败的 但选择辛德勒作为英雄是正确的选择
It is precisely by focusing on a German who did something to help the Jews, that one demonstrates how it was possible to do something,
正是通过聚焦于一个帮助犹太人的德国人 才能展示出是有可能做些什么的
and thus to condemn those who did nothing, claiming that the regime was so totalitarian, it was not possible to do anything, and so on.
从而谴责那些什么也没做的人 这些人声称这个体制是如此的极权 无法做任何事情等等
In United 93, on the contrary, the focus on the rebellion serves the purpose of preventing us to ask the truly pertinent questions.
相反 在《联航93》中 聚焦于反叛的目的是为了防止我们提出真正相关的问题
That is to say, let us indulge in a simple mental experiment.
也就是说 让我们进行一个简单的心理实验
Let us imagine both films, United 93, World Trade Center with the same change.
让我们想象两部电影 《联航93》和《世界贸易中心》 都做出了同样的改变
Let us say that instead of United 93,
我们说替换成《联航93》的是一部名为《美国11号》的电影
Or let us imagine World Trade Center remade as the story of two of the firefighters or policemen who did die in the rubble of the Twin Towers after postponed prolonged suffering,
或者让我们想象《世界贸易中心》被改编成两名在双子塔废墟中死去的消防员或警察的故事
without in any way justifying the terrible crime or showing an understanding for it.
也即 对这个可怕的罪行 不以任何方式进行合理性的辩护 不以任何方式去表现理解
Such aversion would confront us with the true horror of the situation.
这种转变会让我们面对真正的恐怖情境
It would thus compel us to think, to start asking serious questions about how such a thing could have happened and what does it mean.
因此 它会迫使我们开始思考 提出严肃的问题 关于这样的事情是如何发生的 以及它意味着什么
The second feature, both films restrain not only from taking a political stance about the events, but even from depicting their larger political contacts.
第二个特点是 这两部电影不仅没有采取关于事件的政治立场 甚至没有描述它们更大的政治背景
That is to say, neither the passengers on United 93 flight nor the policemen in World Trade Center have a grasp on the full picture.
也就是说 《联航93》的乘客和《世界贸易中心》的警察都没有完全理解整个情况
All of a sudden, they find themselves thrown into a terrifying situation, and they have to make the best out of it.
他们突然发现自己被扔进了一个可怕的情况中 他们必须尽力而为
This lack of what Frederic Jameson would have called cognitive mapping is crucial.
这很关键 即这种像弗雷德里克·詹姆森所说的认知地图的缺乏
Both films depict ordinary people affected by the sudden brutal intrusion of history with a capital H, the invisible real that hurts.
这两部电影都描绘了普通人受到历史——大写的H——突然残酷侵入的影响 这是不可见的、令人痛苦的真实
All we see are the disastrous effects.
我们所看到的只是灾难性的后果
So that in the case of World Trade Center,
所以在世界贸易中心的这个事件中 人们很容易想象出一个完全相同的电影 其中双子塔的倒塌不是因为恐怖袭击 而是 比方说 由于一场强烈的地震
Or even more problematically, we can imagine the same film,
或者更有问题的是 我们可以想象同一个电影
the same narrative at least, taking place, for example, to be really evil in a big German city
至少是同一个叙事 例如 出于真正的邪恶 在一个德国大城市发生的 比如在1944年冬天 经历了一次毁灭性的盟军轰炸之后
Or even more evil surmise, what about the same film taking place in a bombed high-rise building in southern Beirut during the last Lebanon-Israel conflict?
或者更邪恶的猜想 如果同样的电影发生在上一次黎巴嫩-以色列冲突期间 南贝鲁特被炸的高楼大厦中会怎样
And that's the point.
这就是重点
It cannot take place there.
它不能发生在那里
Such a film taking place in southern Beirut would have been immediately dismissed as a subtle pro-Hezbollah terrorist propaganda or something similar.
这样一部发生在南贝鲁特的电影 会立即被贴上微妙的亲真主党恐怖主义宣传或类似的标签
What this means is that the two films message ideological, political message, resides in their very abstention from delivering a message.
这意味着 这两部电影的信息——意识形态、政治信息 存在于它们所避免传递那些信息中
This abstention is sustained by an implicit trust into one's government.
这种弃权是由于对政府的隐性信任而得以维持的 （译注：即相信政府会处理好相关问题 因此不需要通过电影来传递特定的信息或观点 ）
When the enemy attacks, one just don't think, do your duty.
当敌人攻击时 你作为一个个体 不用去思考 只需去尽你的职责
This is what I call Britney Spears' theory of action.
这就是我所说的布兰妮·斯皮尔斯的行动理论
Because effectively, I remember two years ago, seeing Britney Spears' interview on MTV, She was asked, what does she think about Iraq and so on?
因为实际上 我记得两年前 看布兰妮·斯皮尔斯在MTV的采访 她被问到她怎么看伊拉克等问题
And she said, I don't quite understand it.
她说 我不太明白
All I know is that at a certain point, we ordinary people should simply trust our president.
我所知道的就是 在某些时候 我们普通人应该简单地信任我们的总统
This brings us back to our starting point, to the concrete character of the two films depicting ordinary people in a terse realistic mode.
这把我们带回到起点 到两部电影用简洁现实的方式描绘普通人的具体特征
Now, we philosophers know Kegel's counter-intuitive use of the opposition of abstract and concrete.
现在 我们哲学家知道黑格尔对“抽象”与“具体”的对立的反直觉使用
As you all know in our ordinary language, abstract are general notions, as opposed to concrete, really existing singular objects and events.
如你们都知道 在我们的日常语言中 抽象是指一般概念 与之相对的是具体的、真实存在的单个对象和事件
Talking does not exist.
谈话并不存在
I, maybe, I'm not so sure, exist here now talking to you.
我 也许 我不太确定 现在在这里和你们交谈存在
For Hegel, on the contrary, it is such immediate reality which is abstract.
对于黑格尔来说 恰恰相反 这种直接的现实是抽象的
And to render it concrete means to deploy the complex universal context that gives meaning to it.
要使其具体化 意味着要展开赋予其意义的复杂普遍环境
Let me give you an example which is fictional because I don't smoke.
让我给你们举一个例子 这是虚构的 因为我不吸烟
If I were to smoke here for Hegel, the most abstract approach would have been simply to present me here as this really existing individual smoking.
如果我在这里吸烟 对于黑格尔来说 最抽象的方法是简单地呈现我这个真实存在的个体在这里吸烟
A concrete approach would have been to render visible, to articulate the complex historical, social, economic, ideological context which has to be here so that I can smoke here.
一个具体的方法是 使复杂的历史、社会、经济、意识形态环境可见 清晰地表达出来 这是我能在这里吸烟的必要条件
European colonization of Latin America where, if I am correctly informed, smoking comes
欧洲对拉丁美洲的殖民 如果我消息正确的话 吸烟起源于此
from then the development of industry, plantations, or in a more delicate way, why do we have have to smoke, stress of work, relaxation and so on.
然后是工业、种植园的发展 或者更细腻一点 我们为什么需要吸烟 工作压力、放松等等
All this context has to be here so that this pseudo-concrete reality can happen and that wider context, this is what we call dialectical mediation, is what for Hegel is concrete.
所有这些背景必须存在 这样这种伪具体现实才能发生 而这个更广泛的背景 就是我们所说的辩证中介 对黑格尔来说才是具体的
And back to the two films, here is the problem.
回到这两部电影 这里有个问题
Both are abstract in the Hegelian sense.
两者在黑格尔意义上都是抽象的
The function of their down-to-earth depiction of concrete individuals struggling for life is not just to avoid cheap commercial spectacle, but to obliterate the historical context.
他们对为生存而奋斗的具体个体进行脚踏实地的描绘 其作用不仅仅是为了避免廉价的商业景观 而是为了抹杀历史语境
Here then is where we are five years later, still unable to locate September 11 into a large narrative, to provide some kind of generally acceptable cognitive mapping.
五年后 我们仍然无法将 9 月 11 日纳入一个大的叙述中 以提供某种普遍可接受的认知地图
The third feature.
第三个特点
In both films, there is a key moment which violates the terse realistic style.
在两部电影中 都有一个违反简练写实风格的关键时刻
United 93 starts with kidnappers in a motel room, praying, getting ready.
《联合93》以绑匪在汽车旅馆房间里祈祷、准备开始的场景开头
They look austere, like some kind of angels of death.
他们看起来严肃 就像某种死亡天使
And the first shot, after the title credits, confirms this impression.
而片头字幕后的第一镜头确认了这种印象
It is a panoramic shot from high above, Manhattan in the night, camera moving above the streets, accompanied by the sound of the kidnappers' prayers,
那是一个从高空拍摄的全景镜头 夜晚的曼哈顿 摄像机在街道上方移动 伴随着绑匪祈祷的声音
as if the kidnappers stroll above the city, getting ready to descend on earth to ripe their deadly harvest.
仿佛绑匪在城市上空徘徊 准备降临地面收割他们的致命收成
Similarly, there are no direct shots of the planes hitting the Twin Towers in World Trade Center.
同样 在《世界贸易中心》中也没有直接显示飞机撞向双子塔的镜头
All that we see seconds before the catastrophe is when one of the policemen is on a busy Street, an ominous shadow quickly passing over the crowd there.
我们在灾难发生前的几秒钟看到的所有画面 是一名警察在繁忙的街道上 一道不祥的阴影迅速掠过那里的人群
Of course, we know, retrospectively, the shadow of the first plane seconds before it will hit its target.
当然 我们事后知道 那是第一架飞机在撞击目标前几秒的影子
These shots confirm on both films a strange theological reverberation, as if the attacks were a kind of divine intervention.
这些镜头在两部电影中都确认了一种奇怪的神学回响 仿佛这些袭击是某种神的介入
What do I mean by this?
我这是什么意思
Recall the first reaction of Jerry Falwell and Pat Robertson to the September 11th bombings.
回想一下杰瑞·法维尔和帕特·罗伯逊对9月11日爆炸事件的第一反应
You remember the scandal, of course, because they perceived the bombings as a sign that God lifted up its protection of the United States because of the sinful way of life of contemporary Americans.
你肯定记得那场丑闻 因为他们将轰炸视为一个标志 认为上帝撤回了对美国的保护 原因是当代美国人的罪恶生活方式
They put the blame on hedonist materialism, liberalism, rampant sexuality, basically claiming exactly the same thing as Muslim fundamentalists, that America got what it deserved.
他们将责任归咎于享乐主义的物质主义、自由主义、泛滥的性行为 基本上与穆斯林原教旨主义者声称的完全相同 认为美国罪有应得
Now in a hidden way, I think, United 93 and World Trade Center tend to do the opposite, but within the same frame, to read the September 11th catastrophe as a blessing in disguise,
现在在某种隐藏的方式下 我认为 《联航93》和《世贸中心》倾向于做相反的事情 但在相同的框架内 将9月11日的灾难视为因祸得福
as a divine intervention from above, destined to awaken us from moral slumber and to bring out the best in us.
作为一种来自上方的神圣干预 旨在唤醒我们从道德沉睡中醒来 并激发我们最好的一面
World Trade Center ends with the off-screen works of an anonymous narrator which spells out this message.
《世贸中心》以一位匿名叙述者的台词结束 阐述了这一信息
Terrible events like the Twin Towers destruction bring out in people the worst and the best.
像双子塔被毁这样的可怕事件 在人们中间既能激发出最坏的一面 也能激发出最好的一面
People are shown to be able to do things they would never imagine of being able.
人们被证明能够做他们从未想象过的事情
So it is as if our societies need a major catastrophe in order to resuscitate the spirit of communal solidarity.
因此 我们的社会似乎需要一场重大灾难才能复兴公共团结精神
Now, here things get really interesting.
现在 这里的事情变得非常有趣
They bring us to our topic.
它们引导我们进入我们的主题
I don't think this is anything bad, because I think that if you look in a much more refined, delicate way, these big science fiction catastrophe movies.
我不认为这有什么不好 因为我认为如果你以一种更精细、更微妙的方式来看待这些大型科幻灾难电影
I think that they are one of the last places where we can still discern some kind of utopian socialist element in Hollywood.
我认为它们是好莱坞仍然可以辨识出某种乌托邦社会主义元素的最后几个地方
I always think that this big catastrophe, spectacular destruction that we see is basically a lure.
我总是认为 我们所看到的这种大型灾难、壮观的破坏基本上是一个诱饵
It's here to deceive us.
它在这里是为了欺骗我们
The truly fascinating thing is what happens as a byproduct, the sudden supsurge of solidarity, dedication, communal love, and so on, and so on.
真正迷人的事情是作为副产品发生的事情 那突然涌现的团结、奉献、社区爱等等
And the message is basically, again, a sad one.
这条信息基本上又是一个悲伤的信息
It is that the only way in our society is to imagine this kind of solidarity activity is against the background of a catastrophe.
那就是 在我们的社会中 想象这种团结行为的唯一方式是在灾难的背景下
But now let me move to what really disturbs me in these two films.
但现在让我转移到这两部电影中真正让我感到不安的地方
Implicitly, I claim, they not justify, but how should I put it, contextualize or provide the interpretation of the events as part of some deeper meaning,
隐含的是 我认为 它们并非在为事件提供正当理由 而是在对事件进行一种解释 将其置于某种更深层含义的背景中 或者为其提供一种解读
how should I put it, in the sense of these events really happened in order to awaken us.
该怎么表达呢 从这些事件真的发生是为了唤醒我们的意义上讲
a secret teleology built in them.
他们内置了一种秘密的目的论
They are terrible, but a blessing in disguise.
即 它们是可怕的 但又是因祸得福
Of course, this brings us to certain teleological and theological reading of history, which I think precisely
当然 这给我们带来了对历史的某些目的论和神学解读
if we want to remain faithful to Judeo-Christian legacy, we should unconditionally reject.
我认为 如果我们想保持对犹太基督教遗产的忠诚 我们应该无条件地拒绝这种解读
This, I claim, false teleology best exemplified by that well-known metaphor of a painting.
我认为 这种错误的目的论最好的例证就是著名的绘画隐喻 （译注：在哲学和文学中 这个比喻经常用来描述人们试图解释或理解世界时可能采用的一种方法 这种比喻暗示着将世界看作是一幅画 而我们试图从中找到某种意义或目的 ）
You know, when something appears discordant, terrifying, horrible to us, it is as if we are looking at the painting, the painting being the universe, from we are too close to it.
你知道 就好像我们在看这幅画 这幅画就是宇宙 我们离它太近了 那么其中的某些细节对我们来说显得不和谐、可怕、可怕时
And it appears as a stain.
那些细节就看起就来像是一个污点
Like if you look even at the most beautiful painting, whatever you want, Rembrandt, da Vinci, too close you see a stain.
就像如果你太近地看任何一幅最美的画 无论你想要的是伦勃朗、达芬奇 太近了你会看到一个污点
You withdraw it, you see how what appeared as a stain contributes to global harmony.
你把它拉远 你会看到那些看似污点的东西是如何贡献于整体和谐 （译注：即油画中 只有拉远才能看到整体 拉近看到只有颜料）
But I think that precisely with catastrophes, maybe even much larger, of course, than September 11, like Holocaust, the Stalinist Gulag, and why not?
但我认为 特别是对于灾难 可能甚至比9月11日这种更大的灾难 如大屠杀、斯大林的古拉格——也是如此——
We live in the middle of such a catastrophe.
我们生活在这样一场灾难中
It makes you think why we don't talk more about it.
这让你思考为什么我们不更多地谈论它
You remember this summer, there was a cover story on the Time magazine.
你记得这个夏天 《时代》杂志上有一个封面故事
So it's publicly known that in the last 10 years, at least 4 million people died of unnatural causes in Congo.
所以公众已经知道 在过去的10年里 至少有400万人因非自然原因在刚果死亡
OK, we ignore it.
但我们忽略了它
So this should at least make use of speeches of whenever a humanitarian crisis is discovered,
每当发现人道主义危机时 它们至少会在演讲中用到
The sad lesson is that there is always some political, strategic calculation behind it.
但悲哀的教训是 背后总是有一些政治、战略的计算
But what I want to say, when we witness such a tragedy, let's say Auschwitz, Holocaust,
但我想说的是 当我们目睹这样的悲剧 比如说奥斯威辛 大屠杀
you can feel that it's in a way obscene to say, ah, Auschwitz appears such a tragedy because we are too close to it, we see it as a stain.
你会感觉说 啊 奥斯威辛之所以看起来这么悲惨是因为我们离得太近 所以我们将其视为一个污点 认为它在某种程度上是不道德的
but from a proper distance available only to God, it would be clear how this contributes to global harmony of the universe or whatever.
但如果从一个只有上帝才能达到的适当距离看的话 才能清楚地看到这如何有助于宇宙的全球和谐或其他什么
It's an obscenity.
这是一种亵渎（译注：后文统一将 obscence 译为亵渎 在精神分析中 "obscene" （淫秽的）通常指的是一种精神过程或内容 其性质或表达方式被认为是不适当或不可接受的 "obscene" 并不仅仅指性方面的内容 还可以包括任何违背社会规范或引发不适情绪的内容 ）
What does this mean?
这是什么意思
This means, for example, that we should finally take the lesson of what for me as
例如 这意味着我们最终应该吸取教训
an atheist is absolutely unsurpassable ethical revolution, one of the maybe two, three path-breaking texts, entire human history, the Book of Job in the Bible.
对于作为一个作为无神论者的我来说 有一个绝对是不可超越的伦理革命 放眼整个人类历史中 也仅两、三篇开创性的文本中的一篇 《圣经》中的《约伯记》
Remember what happens there.
想一下它讲了什么 但忽略文本最开始的部分 （译注：即约伯记开头上帝和撒旦的对话）
I think this is just probably taken over from some previous tradition, which is why enemies of Judeo-Christian tradition like to point, you know that obscene conversation, like, you know, God and devil sitting at the table, desserts are served drinks, and then they, oh, what about that guy, blah, blah.
我认为这只是可能从某个早期传统中继承过来的 这就是为什么犹太-基督教传统的敌人喜欢指出 你知道那种令人反感的对话 比如 你知道 上帝和魔鬼坐在桌子旁 甜点被端上 饮料被供应 然后他们说 哦 那个家伙怎么样 等等
That's an obscenity, forget that.
那是亵渎 忘记它
Think about, focus on what happens.
想一想 关注点在于 发生了什么
Job is hit by calamities.
约伯遭遇灾难
And what does Job do?
约伯做了什么
It's incredible how spontaneously we try to falsify his image.
真是令人难以置信 我们如何自发地试图歪曲他的形象
Once I asked my friends, atheist or religious, and most of them had this totally fake memory that Job is a guy who,
有一次我问我的朋友们 无论是无神论者还是宗教信徒 他们大多数人都有这样一个完全虚假的记忆
and there should reside the lesson of the story, who silently suffers, humbly submits to divine will.
认为约伯是个——按照故事的教训——默默承受苦难 谦卑地顺从神的意志的人
Not at all.
根本不是这样
He's angry.
他很愤怒
He protests all the time.
他一直在抗议
But here, also, we should be very precise.
但在这里 我们也应该非常准确
What happens there?
那里发生了什么
He doesn't protest in this vulgar economic sense, I didn't deserve it, blah, blah.
他并不是以这种庸俗的经济意义上抗议 比如我不应该遭受这些 等等
There are three bad guys, three theologists there, who are precisely providers of meaning.
那里有三个坏人 三个神学家 正是意义的提供者 （译注：以利法（Eliphaz）、比勒达（Bildad）和琐法（Zophar） 这三人是约伯在遭受苦难时的朋友 他们前来探望约伯并试图解释约伯所经历的苦难 ）
The point of their, you know, three friends, or four, I'm not going to look at this, three, they don't,
他们的重点——三到四个朋友吧 我不在乎这点——
the point is not that they put the blame on Job, that's secondary, like the first one who provides the simple pseudo-hermeneutics.
重点并不是他们责怪约伯 那是次要的 就像第一个提供简单的伪解释学的人 （译注：伪装成深刻而实际上是错误的解释）
God is just, so if you suffer, even if you are not aware now of what, you must have done something.
就像是 上帝是公正的 所以如果你遭受苦难 即使你现在不知道为什么 你一定做了些什么
No, it's more precise.
不 更准确一些
They just desperately try to provide a meaning.
他们只是拼命试图提供一个意义
Their underlying hypothesis, or axiom, is it must have some meaning, if we know it or not.
他们的基本假设或公理是 这一定有某种意义 无论我们知道与否
And the absolute greatness, that's undescribable ethical revolution, I think, of Job is to reject this meaning.
约伯的绝对伟大 我认为是不可描述的伦理革命 就是拒绝这种意义
I see in this the sense of his bitter insistence.
我在这里看到了他痛苦的坚持
Not I'm good, I'm extra good, I served God, but I didn't deserve it.
不是说 我是个好人 我是个品质优秀的人 我服侍了上帝 但我不应该遭受这些
Again, not in the sense I was good, but in the sense of no, But there is no deeper meaning here.
再次强调 不是因为我是个好人 而是因为没有 是因为这里没有更深层的意义
And remember what happens then when God finally intervenes.
记住当上帝最终介入时发生了什么
He gives full right to Job.
他完全支持约伯
He says to the three, quick ideologies, quickly, to the three, like maybe the name of one of them was, I don't know, one was Pat, the other was Jerry, who knows who was the third one.
他对那三个草率的意识形态 草率的 对那三个 比如其中一个的名字可能是 我不知道 一个叫帕特 另一个叫杰瑞 谁知道第三个是谁
And he says, no, against them.
他说 不 他们错了 （译注：“耶和华对约伯说话以后 就对提幔人以利法说  我的怒气向你和你两个朋友发作 因为你们议论我 不如我的仆人约伯说的是  ”）
So I think, again, that today this pressure of meaning is strong.
所以我认为 再次地 今天这种意义的压力是很大的
And now, my god, I will speak like a kind of a biblical preacher.
现在 我的天哪 我将像一位圣经布道者一样讲话
But I mean it sincerely, in the sense of beware of succumbing to this pressure.
但我是真诚的 即要谨防屈服于这种压力
I mean it seriously.
我是认真的
This is where the devil waits upon you.
这就是魔鬼等待你的地方
This is paganism, pagan universe, as all intelligent, not only Protestants, but Catholic also, like Chesterton pointed out.
这是异教 异教宇宙 正如所有聪明人 不仅是新教徒 天主教徒也一样 就像切斯特顿指出的
You know, this universal hermeneutic attitude, this metaphoric reading of the universe.
你知道 这种普遍的解释态度 这种对宇宙的隐喻阅读
This rose, that rose, cat is not a cat, it's devil, the dog is, you know, like this fullness of meaning, no, this is not Judeo-Christian legacy.
这朵玫瑰 那朵玫瑰 猫不是猫 它是魔鬼 狗是 你知道 就像这种意义的多样、丰满 不 这不是犹太教和基督教的遗产
Judeo-Christian legacy is much more bitter.
犹太-基督教的遗产要苦涩得多
You accept the meaninglessness of the universe.
你接受宇宙的无意义
And today, again, it's a danger to succumb to this pseudo-hermeneutics when we witness things like AIDS, the prospect of ideological catastrophe, and so on.
而今天 再次 屈服于这种伪解释学是一种危险 当我们见证到像艾滋病、意识形态灾难的前景等事情时
It's so simple to succumb to this temptation.
屈服于这种诱惑是如此简单
AIDS, oh, it must have some meaning, punishment for this ecology, yes, because we disturbed the balance of yin yang and so on or whatever.
艾滋病 哦 它一定有某种意义 对当前的情形的惩罚 是的 因为我们打破了阴阳的平衡等等或其他什么
And no, you start with a little bit of hermeneutic of ecology, I warn you.
不 你从一点点生态的解释学开始 我警告你
You end up in Da Vinci Code, no?
你最终会陷入《达芬奇密码》 不是吗 （译注：如果你开始从生态学的角度解释一些事物 然后过度解读 可能会导致跟《达·芬奇密码》一样的结果 即进入了一些不切实际或不合理的推断、猜测或陈词滥调中 ）
And then you end up with Jesus Christ copulating, you know?
然后你最终会得出与耶稣基督交配 你知道吗 （译注：得到荒诞的结果）
It's a small step from one to the other, no?
从一边到另一边只是一小步 不是吗
So again, one has to resist this temptation, which is a terrible temptation.
所以再次 人必须抵抗这种诱惑 这是一个可怕的诱惑
Let me give you a brutal, extreme example,
让我给你一个残酷的 极端的例子
which I not like, but it's at least convincing.
我不喜欢 但至少是令人信服的
When I was in Israel, I was told that there is a minor sect, but nonetheless not negligible, quite strong, sect of people.
当我在以色列时 有人告诉我有一个小型教派 是不可忽视 相当强大的一群人
And there is a rabbi who leads them who believe that, among other things, that Holocaust was justified, that the Jewish people, European Jews, did something very sinful.
有一个拉比领导他们 他们相信 包括其他事物在内 大屠杀是合理的 欧洲的犹太人 犯了非常严重的罪
OK, he tries to specify it as integrating themselves too much into European societies, and that this was divine punishment.
好吧 他试图具体说明 就是他们过于融入欧洲社会 这是神的惩罚
It's terrible, but I understand it in the sense that even if the message is a bad one, we deserved it.
这很糟糕 但我的理解是 即使这个消息是坏消息 也是我们应得的
Often, it's better a bad message than no message.
通常 坏消息总比没有消息要好
Because even if the message is bad, what you nonetheless gain is a dialogue with the meaningful universe.
因为即使消息是坏的 你仍然获得的是与有意义的宇宙的对话
It still means things have a global meaning, and so on, and so on.
它仍然意味着事物具有整体性的意义 等等
So that's my first theoretical point.
所以那是我的第一个理论观点
Let's go now on.
现在我们继续
Undoubtedly, at least some of you, if we were to be immediately in a dialogue, would have reacted to what I've said, saying, but this is not what I directly or how I directly experienced the film.
毫无疑问 至少有些人 如果我们立刻进行对话 可能会对我所说的内容产生反应 说 但对于这部电影 我不这样去体验 我也没有体验到这些
It's not open.
它并非开放的
Yes.
是的
And now I come to my second crucial point.
现在我来谈谈我的第二个关键点
The level at which this logic operates, this obscene, I claim, beliefs, it must have had a meaning, is not the level of our explicit beliefs.
我认为 对这种逻辑运作的看待方式 这种亵渎的信念 它一定有某种意义 不是我们对明确的信念的看待方式
It's the level of what?
它是哪种看待方式
I will describe this level now, briefly referring to what I developed in some of my books.
我现在将描述这个方式 简要参考我书中的一些内容
Namely, I would like, in case of professional solidarity, referring to a philosopher who, three days ago, lost his job,
我想在处于职业团结的情况下 提及一个哲学家 他在三天前失去了工作
referred to a well-known contemporary American philosopher who elaborated the relationship between what we know and what we don't know.
他提到了一位著名的当代美国哲学家 该哲学家阐述了我们所知道的与我们所不知道的之间的关系
You got the point.
你明白了
Sorry, old joke, Donald Trump.
抱歉 老笑话 唐纳德·特朗普
No, I mean, I'm referring to, you remember in March 2003,
我的意思是 我指的是 你记得在2003年3月
Donald Rumsfeld gave the famous interview where he developed his thoughts on the relationship between known and unknown.
唐纳德·拉姆斯菲尔德在一次著名的采访中发展了他关于已知与未知之间关系的思想
Here it is, the quote.
以下是引用
There are known knowns.
有已知的已知
There are things we know that we know.
有一些事情 我们知道“我们知道它”
That's clear.
这很清楚
Like, I don't know.
比如 我不知道
I'm here at Calvin College, and I know that I'm here.
我在加尔文学院 我知道我在这里
I know that I know that.
我也知道“我知道我在这里”
Then he goes on, there are known unknowns.
然后他继续说 有已知的未知
That is to say, there are things that we know we don't know.
也就是说 有一些事情 我们知道“我们不知道他们”
This is also clear.
这也很清楚
Like, I know there are some cars outside this building, but I don't know how many cars are parked there.
比如 我知道这栋楼外面有一些车 但我不知道那里停了多少辆车
And I know that I don't know this.
我也知道“我不知道那里停了多少辆车”
That is to say, this is something that I don't know, but it's still, how should I put it,
也就是说 这是我不知道的事情 但是 怎么说呢
with regard to the horizon of understanding or of meaning, It's still within the field of my knowledge.
从理解的视域或者说意义的视域来说 还是在我的知识范围之内的
I clearly don't know that I know that.
我清楚地不知道我所知的东西 （译注：即 清楚地意识到自己并不知道自己已经掌握了哪些信息 上面的这段话类似于“知之为知之 不知为不知 是知也”中 最后的“知”是对之前的“知”的进一步反思 即对思考本身的思考）
Then Rumsfeld goes on.
然后拉姆斯菲尔德继续说
This was, of course, destined at that point to warn us of unpredictable horrors hidden in Iraq.
这当然是在那个时候旨在警告我们伊拉克隐藏的不可预测的恐怖
But there are also unknown unknowns.
但还有未知的未知
There are things we don't know that we don't know.
有我们不知道我们不知道的事情
It's also clear.
这也很清楚
Let us say if Saddam were to have some ultra-secret weapon or whatever, not the ordinary weapons of mass destruction that we suspected that he had.
比方说 如果萨达姆拥有某种超级秘密武器或其他东西 不是我们怀疑他拥有的普通大规模杀伤性武器
This would be unknown unknowns.
这将是未知的未知
It's not simply that we didn't know.
这不仅仅是我们不知道
We even wouldn't have known that we don't know.
我们甚至不会知道我们不知道
Because it's totally outside our horizon.
因为它完全在我们的视野之外
But here, unfortunately, the dialectical strength of Rumsfeld thinking finds its limit.
但在这里 不幸的是 拉姆斯菲尔德思考的辩证强度找到了它的极限
Because did you notice that the fourth term is missing?
因为你注意到第四个术语缺失了吗
We have known knowns.
我们有已知的已知
We have known unknowns we know that we don't know, and we have unknown unknowns.
我们有已知的未知 我们知道我们不知道 我们有未知的未知
It's so much outside our horizon that we don't know that we don't know.
它在我们的视野之外 以至于我们不知道我们不知道
What about the fourth term, which I claim is the most interesting one?
那第四个术语呢 我声称是最有趣的一个
Not the known unknowns, but the unknown knowns, things we know, but we don't even know that we know them.
不是“已知的未知” 而是“未知的已知” 那些我们知道 但我们甚至不知道我们知道它们的东西
That is to say, this is ideology.
也就是说 这就是意识形态
Ideology is not so much our explicit thesis.
意识形态并不是我们的明确论点那么简单
Today, of course, belief, as everybody says in hedonist, cynical era, nobody's ready to fight for big causes.
今天 当然 正如每个人在享乐主义、愤世嫉俗的时代所说 没有人准备为大事业而战
What I claim is that, nonetheless, there are, more than ever maybe, beliefs here, beliefs which,
我声称 尽管如此 这里有比以往任何时候都多的信仰 这些信仰
although we would never publicly admit that they are our beliefs, we, as it were, practice these beliefs.
虽然我们永远不会公开承认这些是我们的信仰 但我们事实上在实践这些信仰
They are embodied in our knowledge, in the materials we use, and so on, and so on.
它们体现在我们的知识中 在我们使用的材料中 等等
And to end up to just make the last mention of poor Rumsfeld, I think that that's why he lost his job.
最后 只是提一下可怜的拉姆斯菲尔德 我认为这就是他失去工作的原因
Because he didn't know what he knows.
因为他不知道他所知道的
OK, to put it in more consistent way, knowing quite serious, why did things in Iraq go wrong?
好吧 更一致地说 为什么伊拉克的事情出了问题
Precisely because American politics was not aware of its unknown knowns, of the implicit ideological prejudices, presuppositions, which they were simply here,
正是因为美国政治不知道它的未知已知 即隐含的意识形态偏见、预设 它们就在这里
not even you are aware of them, but they regulate your activity.
你甚至都没有意识到它们 但它们调控着你的行动
You know, like presuppositions about how everybody in the world likes American type of democracy, presuppositions about how the people will react in Iraq, and so on, and so on, and so on.
你知道 像是关于“世界上每个人都喜欢美国式民主”的预设 关于伊拉克人民会如何反应的预设 等等 等等
So this level is, I think, crucial for the functioning of ideology.
所以这个层面 我认为 对意识形态的运作至关重要
All these things that, and this is the crucial problem of belief, I claim.
所有这些事情 这是我认为的信仰的关键问题
All these things that we, in a way, believe without believing.
所有这些我们在某种程度上相信而又不真正相信的事情
In my book, The Parallax View, I developed more in detail.
在我的书《视差观》中 我更详细地展开了这个话题
I will just mention it here.
我在这里只是简单提一下
The wonderful example, which I found in a biography of Niels Bohr, of Copenhagen quantum physics.
尼尔斯·玻尔的一个精彩例子 我在他的传记中找到 他是哥本哈根量子物理学派的一份子
Niels Bohr, incidentally, was also the guy who, I think, provided a wonderful right answer to Einstein.
顺便说一下 尼尔斯·玻尔也是那个我认为给了爱因斯坦一个绝妙正确回答的人
You know that Einstein's well-known phrase, which reflects his distrust in quantum physics,
你知道爱因斯坦那句著名的话 反映了他对量子物理的不信任
God doesn't play dice.
上帝不掷骰子
Everybody knows this.
每个人都知道这句话
But you know what was Niels Bohr's answer?
但你知道尼尔斯·玻尔的回答是什么吗
Don't tell God what to do.
不要告诉上帝该做什么
I mean, it's correct.
我的意思是 这回答是正确的
OK, this is even a more beautiful story.
好吧 这还有一个更美妙的故事
A friend visited Nils Bohr in a countryside house.
一个朋友拜访尼尔斯·玻尔在乡下的房子
And notice above the entrance door, a horseshoe.
并注意到入口门上方有一个马蹄铁
In Europe, I don't know how it is here, a horseshoe is kind of a superstitious item.
在欧洲 我不知道这里怎么样 马蹄铁是一种迷信物品
If you put it above the entrance, it is supposed to keep out the evil spirits and keep the house safe, whatever.
如果你把它放在入口上方 据说可以防止邪恶的灵魂进入 保持房子安全等等
Now the friend was shocked and addressed Nils Bohr.
现在朋友很震惊 并向尼尔斯·玻尔提出了问题
My god, I thought you are a scientist.
我的天哪 我以为你是个科学家
Do you believe in this kind of superstitious crap?
你相信这种迷信的废话吗
Nils Bohr answered, no, of course not.
尼尔斯·玻尔回答说 不 当然不
I'm not crazy.
我不迷信 我没有丧失理智
Then the other guy says, but why is it there then?
然后那个人说 但它为什么会在那儿呢
Here Nils Bohr gave the correct answer.
这时尼尔斯·玻尔给出了正确的答案
Not the usual boring, fake, multiculturalist tolerant one that we like today.
不是我们今天喜欢的那种乏味的、假的、多元文化的宽容答案
It's just our way of life.
这只是我们的生活方式
It is out of respect for and so on.
这是出于尊重等等
I know this story.
我知道这个故事
All my Jewish friends, they don't believe in kosher food,
我所有的犹太朋友 他们不相信洁食 （译注："Kosher food" 是指符合犹太教教规的食物 即符合《利未记》和《申命记》中规定的食物准则）
But they don't eat pork out of respect for, and so on, no.
但他们出于尊重等等 不吃猪肉 （这个故事）不是这样
And you get here wonderful paradoxes.
你会在这里得到奇妙的悖论
I mean, I'm not focusing on Jews with Arabs.
我的意思是 我不是只针对犹太人和阿拉伯人
It's the same with us Christians.
我们基督徒也是一样
I'm saying because I know the situation there.
我这么说是因为我知道那边的情况
A typical Jew, of course, doesn't believe in God.
一个典型的犹太人 当然不相信上帝
But nonetheless, he believes that God gave them the land of Israel, that they can have it.
但尽管如此 他相信上帝给了他们以色列的土地 他们可以拥有它
That's another story, no?
那是另一个故事 不是吗
But what I want to say is, so what is then the answer, not this politically correct, of Nils Bohr?
但我想说的是 那么尼尔斯·玻尔的答案是什么 不是这种政治正确的答案
Why do you have it?
你为什么需要它
It's a wonderful one.
这是一个精彩的答案
He answered, of course, I don't believe in it.
他回答说 当然 我不相信它
But I have it there because I was told that it works even if you don't believe in it.
但我把它挂在那里是因为我被告知 即使你不相信它 它也会起作用
That's ideology today.
这就是今天的意识形态
You don't have to believe in democracy.
你不必真的相信民主
You practice it.
你实践它
And your beliefs are out there in practice.
而你的信仰体现在实践中
Let me give you, let's go to the end here.
让我给你举个例子 我们来结束这个话题
It will be, as it's usual with me, I'm sorry if I offend some of you, an absolutely scatological, obscene end point.
像往常一样 我要以一个绝对粗俗、亵渎的终结来结束 如果我冒犯了你们中的一些人 我很抱歉
but I cannot resist repeating an old story that I often use.
但我忍不住要重复一个我经常用的老故事
If you had the fortune of misfortune to travel around Europe, maybe you noticed how, in what different way,
如果你有幸或不幸游历过欧洲 也许你注意到了 在欧洲 厕所的结构方式有何不同
now comes the dangerous point, toilets are structured in Europe.
现在来到了危险的点 厕所是如何构造的
You have the French toilets where the hole where excrement disappears is in the back.
你有法式厕所 其中排泄物消失的洞在后面
So the idea is it drops, falls directly into it, it goes away as soon as possible.
所以理念是它直接掉进去 尽快消失
Then you have English or yours, Anglo-Saxon, where it floats in water.
然后你有英式或你们的盎格鲁-撒克逊式 其中它在水中漂浮
Then you have the German one, which is the most obscene, of course, which is that the hole is in front.
然后你有德式的 当然是最亵渎的 洞在前面
And you have just a little bit of water in the hole so that most of the bowl is a kind of a plateau.
洞里只有一点点水 所以那个碗状物的大部分是一个平台
The idea is your excrement falls there to enable.
理念是你的排泄物落在那里 以便能
It's an old, disgusting German tradition that every morning you should inspect your bowl, sniff it, and so on to see, look for any traces of illness.
这是一个古老的、令人厌恶的德国传统 每天早上你应该检查你的排泄物 嗅它 等等 以寻找任何疾病的迹象
If you don't believe me, go and look.
如果你不相信我 去看看
It's quite a cultural shock.
It's quite a cultural shock.
Now I ask myself, why this?
现在我问自己 为什么会这样
What's the point?
这是为了什么
I read books.
我读过书
There are two books on the market,
市面上有两本书
so you can check it on architect, very obscene books.
所以你可以在建筑上查证 非常亵渎的书
They have scientific studies.
它们进行了科学研究
In what angle shit falls down.
关于粪便以何种角度落下（比较好）
And they don't give an account of this.
他们没有对此做出解释
They simply eat every book that I know or text plays this simple utilitarian card.
它们简单地在每本我所知道的书或文本中打出这张简单的“功利主义牌”
Oh, how is that the other guys don't see that ours is the most utilitarian, the most practical?
哦 其他人怎么就没看出我们的是最为功利、最实用的呢
But then it strike me.
但然后我意识到
Of course, things are more complex in reality.
当然 现实中的事情更为复杂
But basically, I claim this is the only account that I can imagine.
但基本上 我认为这是我能想到的唯一解释
Do you know that, if you know a little bit of the history of European thought, around the time of Hegel, it was popular to claim that, to assert the notion of so-called European Trinity.
你知道吗 如果你对欧洲思想史有所了解 在黑格尔时代左右 流行声称所谓的“欧洲三位一体”的概念
The idea being that Europe, as a spiritual entity, is structured around three poles.
这个观点是 作为一个精神实体的欧洲 围绕三个极点构建
Each of them stands for a certain nation, for a certain political attitude or attitude towards life, and for a certain level of social life.
每一个极点代表一个特定的国家 一个特定的政治态度或对生活的态度 以及一个特定的社会生活层面
Germans are politically conservative, the level of life is poetry, thinking, contemplation.
德国人在政治上保守 生活方式是诗歌、思考、沉思
French, politics, level of life, domain of life, politically leftist, revolutionary.
法国 政治 生活方式 生活领域 政治左派 革命
English. Economy as a sphere of life and moderate liberalism.
英国 经济是生活的一个领域 温和的自由主义
It did strike me, but that's it.
它确实让我意识到 就是这样
The French approach this radical politics.
法国人采取这种激进的政治方法
It falls in, liquidated, disappears.
它掉进去 被消解 消失
It's like guillotine.
这就像断头台
It should disappear.
它应该消失
Anglo-Saxon, pragmatic.
盎格鲁-撒克逊 实用主义
Let it flow there.
让它在那儿流淌
We will solve the problem.
我们会解决问题
Germans, of course, poetry and contemplation.
德国人 当然 诗歌和沉思
Now, crazy as this may sound, but believe me or not, in a way it is true that I say, that's my point, serious point that I want to make.
现在 这听起来可能很疯狂 但不管你信不信 某种程度上这是真的 我要说的 这是我想要表达的严肃观点
It's easy to say, oh, no ideology and so on.
很容易说 哦 没有意识形态等等
My God, you go to the toilet and you sit on ideology, how should I put it.
我的天哪 你去厕所时 你就坐在意识形态上 我该怎么表达呢
That is to say, even such the lowest of the lowest vulgar everyday object cannot be accounted for in direct utilitarian terms.
也就是说 即使是这种最低俗、最日常的物品也不能用直接的功利主义术语来解释
It is structured like this because it's the most appropriate but embodies certain very fundamental attitudes towards what is one of the big problems of life,
它是这样构造的 因为它是最合适的 但体现了对生命中一个大问题的一些非常基本的态度
what to do with this embarrassing excrement that comes out of our body.
那就是如何处理从我们身体里排出的令人尴尬的排泄物
And this is not a secondary point.
这不是一个次要的观点
Every good anthropologist will tell you that one of the signs that you are dealing with humans no longer with apes or animals is that you have this embarrassment what to do with feet, basically.
每一个好的人类学家都会告诉你 你能区分人类和猿类或其他动物的一个标志就是你对如何处理粪便有这种尴尬感
It must disappear.
它必须消失
It's the whole problem of, I mean, we are immediately in the deepest metaphysics.
这是整个问题的所在 我的意思是 我们立刻进入了最深奥的形而上学
I'm quite serious, which is, what we as humans,
我是相当认真的 那就是 作为人类
I think that disgust is a deeply human emotion.
我认为厌恶是一种深刻的人类情感
And what is disgust?
什么是厌恶
Disgust is not necessarily immediately characterized by its object.
厌恶并不一定立即以其对象为特征 （译注：当人们感到厌恶时 不一定是因为直接接触到某个特定的对象）
It has to do something with the disturbed frontier between inside and outside.
它与内外界之间被扰乱的边界有关
Disgust is with something inside, from your inside, you confront it from the outside.
厌恶是来自你内部的某种东西 你从外部与之对抗 （译注：厌恶是源自个体内部的某种东西 但个体将其视为来自外部的对象而与之对抗 换句话说 个体可能会将自己内部的不愉快或不受欢迎的感觉投射到外部环境或对象上 从而产生了厌恶情绪 ）
OK, now you can tell me, but shit is disgusting.
好的 现在你可以告诉我 粪便很恶心
No, but let's take a more neutral example, which I hope will convince you.
不 但让我们来看一个更中性的例子 我希望这能说服你
You have saliva all the time in your mouth.
你的嘴里一直有唾液
You swallow it now all the time, no problem, nothing disgusting.
你现在一直在吞咽它 没问题 没有什么恶心的
Do, or rather, don't do it.
做 或者更确切地说 不要做
I can't do it.
我做不到
But try to do a certain extremely elementary example.
但试着做一个极其简单的示例
Take a glass, spit in it, kind of a certain strata, a half an inch of your saliva, look, and then try to drink it.
拿一个玻璃杯 往里吐唾液 让它有一定的高度 半英寸厚的你的唾液 看看 然后试着喝它
You cannot, because it's outside.
你做不到 因为它在外面
It's disgusting.
这很恶心
So what I want to say is that you cannot imagine how much this tells us about human identity.
所以我想说的是 你无法想象这对我们了解人类身份意味着多少
The point being that at a certain level, precisely at the level of Rumsfeldian unknown knowns,
关键在于 在某种层面 确切地说是在拉姆斯菲尔德式的未知已知层面
we do not perceive ourselves in this most elementary phenomenological self-experience, we do not perceive ourselves as beings with depth.
我们没有在这种最基本的现象学自我体验中感知自己 我们没有将自己视为有深度的存在
The depth is spiritual, not bodily.
深度是精神的 而非身体的
I claim that when I look at you,
我认为 当我看着你时
I somehow obstruct the fact that beneath your skin there are pretty horrible things, all the blood, bones, whatever.
我在某种程度上忽视了你皮肤下面有许多可怕的东西 所有的血液、骨头等等
When I look you into your eyes, head, I behave as if there is some kind of a soul spiritual presence inside, not the stupidity of biological machine or whatever.
当我直视你的眼睛、你的头时 我表现得好像里面有某种灵魂或精神的存在 而不是生物机器或其他什么的愚蠢东西
So this tells us a lot about this most immediate phenomenology of our experience.
所以这告诉了我们很多关于我们经验中最直接的现象学的信息
Again, the way it is embodied in this unknown knowns.
再次强调 这种方式体现在所谓的未知已知中
Now, let me make a step further.
现在 让我进一步阐述
And the central mystery here is that these beliefs, even if we are aware of them, another way that we deal with them is that we transpose them onto others.
这里的核心奥秘是 这些信仰 即使我们意识到它们 我们处理它们的另一种方式是将它们投射到别人身上
There is nothing hypocritical in it, or rather it's a kind of sincere hypocrisy.
这其中没有什么虚伪 或者说这是一种真诚的虚伪
What do we mean by this?
这是什么意思
My favorite example here is another one which I repeatedly use in my books.
我在这里的最爱例子是另一个我在书中所反复使用的
Do you know the Tibetan praying meals?
你知道藏式转经轮吗
Like, you write a prayer, you put it into a meal, you turn it around, or even better,
比如 你写下一个祈祷文 放入转经轮 转动它 或者更好
you put it on a windmill, and it turns around itself.
你把它放在风车上 它自己转动
And to put it in a slightly cynical way, it's wonderful.
稍微讽刺地说 这很棒
Like, you can think about sex, whatever you want, but objectively, you pray, no?
比如 你可以在同时想象性爱 或者任何你想的 但客观上 你在祈祷 不是吗
It prays for you.
它为你祈祷
Now, you will say, ha ha, this goes for primitive cultures.
现在 你会说 哈哈 这适用于原始文化
No, we have exactly same phenomena all around. Think about what, if you ask me, is one of the great contributions of American civilization to world culture, can laughter on TV.
不 我们周围到处都是完全相同的现象 想想美国文明对世界文化的伟大贡献之一 电视上的罐头笑声
You know, laughter being part of the soundtrack.
你知道 笑声成为了配乐的一部分
It's a very mysterious phenomenon.
这是一个非常神秘的现象
Why does it work?
为什么它会起作用
Namely, how does it work?
它是如何起作用的
It's not as many people think that it's It's a kind of a Pavlovian reflex machine to signal you when to laugh.
它不像许多人认为的那样 是一种巴甫洛夫式的反射机制 用来提示你何时该笑
No, as a rule, you don't laugh.
不 通常你不会笑
You return home in the evening, tired as a dog, you put it on, cheers, friends, whatever, you hear the laughter and you just look at it as an idiot and when it ends, you feel relieved.
你晚上累得跟狗一样回家 打开电视 《欢乐时光》、《老友记》或其他 你听到笑声 你就像个白痴那样看着它 当它结束时 你感到轻松
It is as if you have laughed.
就好像你笑过一样
I mean, it's a paradox how, first to put
我的意思是 这是个悖论 首先要说明
I mean, even the most intimate, spontaneous expression of yourself, like laughter, can be transposed onto others.
我的意思是 即使是最亲密、最自发的自我表达 比如笑声 也可以转移到他人身上
The same goes also especially, I claim, for example, for beliefs.
同样的道理 我认为 对于信仰而言也是如此
What do I mean by this?
我的意思是什么
Did you notice how often in families where parents have belief or stop believing, what What happens is that they desperately cling to another one.
你是否注意到 在那些父母有信仰 （而自己）停止信仰的家庭中 经常会发生这样的情况 即他们拼命依附于另一个人
It can be their parents, old mother, children, who should believe.
这个人可以是他们的父母、年迈的母亲、或者的孩子 是这些本应该有信仰的人
What really breaks them down is that much more than their disbelief is to discover that this other, whose innocence should be protected, doesn't believe.
真正让他们崩溃的是 发现这个其他人 本应有着被保护下的天真的人 却没有去信仰
for many people who participate in sexual orgies and so on.
对于许多参与性狂欢等活动的人来说 这比他们自己的不信仰更加让人沮丧
I spoke recently with a sociologist who investigated this and told me how, as a rule, there can be ruthless group orgies, whatever you want, but they always have somebody who should remain innocent, who shouldn't know about it.
我最近与一位社会学家交谈过 他对此进行了调查 并告诉我 在尽情的群体狂欢或其他之类种 有一条规则 他们总希望会有一些人应该保持天真 不应该知道这件事
The moment that happens, their life literally falls apart.
那一刻发生时 他们的生活在字面上崩溃了
This structure, I think, is extremely interesting.
我认为这种结构极其有趣
Let me give you another example from literature.
让我给你举个文学中的另一个例子
Okay, literature, I only saw the film, the Edith Wharton's Age of Innocence.
好的 文学 我只看过电影 《纯真年代》——伊迪丝·华顿的作品——
This is the beauty of the story that you remember, the affair between Newland and that Count Olenskauer who?
这个故事的美在于你记得 纽兰和那个奥伦斯卡尔伯爵夫人之间的恋情吗
No.
不
But the wife, to put it in human terms, Winona Ryder, the young wife
但是妻子 用人类的话说 薇诺娜·瑞德饰演的年轻妻子
is supposed to be naive not to know.
应该是天真的 不知道真相
And then you know what happens at the end.
然后你知道最后发生了什么
The wife, young wife of the hero dies.
英雄的年轻妻子去世了
He thinks he is free now legally to rejoin his love of of Longyear's mistress, Michelle Pfeiffer in the film,
他认为自己现在从法律上来说可以重归多年的爱人 电影中的米歇尔·菲佛
then at this very point, his son tells him that the wife knew it all the time, just pretended not to know, and it's ruined.
就在这个时刻 他的儿子告诉他 妻子一直都知道这一切 只是假装不知道 一切都毁了
He cannot do it.
他无法这样做
You see, he was engaged in this transgressive behavior, whatever, but on condition that another one, of this innocence of another one.
你看 他从事这种越轨行为 但前提是另一个人的纯真
So this is the great mystery of how, even if we don't believe, we claim to be cynical and so on, we have this need for another one to remain pure to believe.
所以这是个伟大的谜团 即使我们不信仰 我们声称自己是愤世嫉俗的 等等 但我们需要另一个人保持纯洁、有信仰
I know now enough of jokes.
我现在知道的笑话够多了
I know a much more serious and tragic version of this.
我知道一个更为严肃和悲惨的版本
Agnes Heller, probably unknown to almost all of you, is a Hungarian philosopher who was during, now she's a very old lady, during World War II in, I think it was even Auschwitz.
阿格尼丝·赫勒 可能你们几乎都不知道 是一位匈牙利哲学家 在二战期间——现在她已经是位非常老的女士——在奥斯威辛集中营
I mean, she has all these numbers, the real one, how should I put it.
我的意思是 她有所有这些编号（译注：集中营对于其中每个犹太人会刺上编号） 真实的
And she told me a very interesting story, how in every barrack in the camp, there were two types of people, basically.
她告诉我一个非常有趣的故事 关于集中营中的每个兵营里基本上有两类人
There were survivalists, those who were totally bitter, but still struggled for survival.
有那些生存者 那些完全痛苦但仍为生存而挣扎的人
And this was some kind of a codified egotism.
有一些默认的利己主义 比如
You were allowed, if the other guy was stupid and left some food there and walked away, you were allowed to steal it.
如果另一个人愚蠢地留下了一些食物然后走开了 你是可以去偷的
There were some minimal rules, but very hard rules.
当然 还有一些最基本的规则 但是非常严格
Then there were so-called Muslims, Muslim men, and the living dead.
然后有所谓的“穆斯林” 即行尸走肉
The ones who simply no longer cared, just as living dead walked around.
那些简直不再关心、就像行尸走肉一样四处走动的人
And then, now comes the tragic point, story she told me.
然后 现在来到了悲剧性的故事 她告诉我的
Then there was in every barrack a myth that somewhere out there, usually in a next barrack, next,
然后每个兵营都有一个传说 通常在下一个兵营里
There is somebody who is still fully human.
有一个人仍然完全是人
That is to say, somebody who didn't regress to this level of survivalism.
也就是说 有人没有退化到这种生存主义的层面
Still, you do that.
也许你仍然会去自立求生
You just cruelly try to survive.
你只是残酷地试图生存
But who behaves even in those terrifying circumstances as if you are in normal life.
但是在那些可怕的环境下 有人仍然表现得好像在正常生活中一样
He helped others, shared food, and so on.
他帮助他人 分享食物等等
And she told me something very interesting, that the most dangerous moment for your psychic integrity was when, as unfortunately it was the case,
她告诉我一件非常有趣的事情 那就是当你发现这只是一个神话时 对你的心理完整性来说是最危险的时刻 不幸的是 这种情况迟早会发生
you sooner or later discovered that this is a myth, that this other is like most of us.
你迟早会发现这个他人和我们大多数人一样
At that point, usually people lose even the will to survive, even this will to struggle and regress to what was called Muslim, Muslimen, that is to say, turned into living dead.
在那一点上 人们通常会失去生存的意愿 甚至是挣扎的意愿 退化成所谓的“穆斯林” 也就是说 变成行尸走肉
So you see the nice here.
所以你看到了这里的美
Even, to put it in more almost theological terms, even to be consistently evil, you need a presupposed goodness somewhere up there.
甚至可以用更接近神学的术语来说 即使是要一贯地邪恶 你也需要假定某处有善良存在
And I claim, now we shouldn't underestimate this.
我认为 我们不应该低估这一点
Now don't go into this orgy, oh, divine spark, we are all deeply good.
现在不要陷入这种狂欢 哦 神圣的火花 我们都在内心深处是善良的
No, the problem is that the same holds for Hitler, for Stalin, from whoever you want.
不 问题在于 对于希特勒、斯大林 无论你想到谁 同样的规则也适用
I have no doubts that they were doing with this innocence in view.
我毫不怀疑 他们是在考虑这种纯真的前提下行事的
That is to say, you can also give to this a very nasty term, unethical term.
也就是说 你也可以给这一个非常令人不快的、不道德的名词
You have, for example, with Stalinist communists, even more in this case with Nazis, this especially perverse logic,
例如 对于斯大林主义的共产主义者 尤其在这种情况下 对于纳粹 这种特别的扭曲逻辑
which is that the greatest heroism when tough things have to be done, you kill, you torture, and so on, that through every idiot can be good.
即 最伟大的英雄主义是当必须做出艰难的事情时 你杀戮 你折磨等等
The greatest heroism is to do the necessary tough, cruel thing to protect the innocence of the others.
每一个傻子都能够去做好事 但最伟大的英雄主义是为了保护他人的纯真而做必要的艰难、残酷的事情
If you look at one of the most disgusting ethical documents, but it's still an ethical document in the sense that crazy as it sounds, it tries to articulate the ethics of 20th century,
如果你看一下最令人厌恶的伦理文档 但它仍然是一份伦理文档 因为它尽管听起来疯狂 试图阐述20世纪的伦理
The famous speech in 33 October, 43, I think, of Heinrich Himmler, SS, had two officers for the preparation of Holocaust in Posen, a Polish city.
海因里希·希姆莱 党卫军 1943年10月在波兰城市波森为准备大屠杀给党卫军军官的那个著名演讲
He there uttered these famous phrases, claiming that Holocaust will be the most glorious chapter of German history, but the chapter which, unfortunately, will never be written.
他在那里发表了这些著名的话语 声称大屠杀将是德国历史上最光荣的章节 但不幸的是 这一章永远不会被写下
That is to say, the message is we are the true heroes.
也就是说 他想表达的是 我们是真正的英雄
It's a terrible message.
这是一个可怕的信息
The message is you are in front of, I mean, in a way, Himmler, that's the horror of it, was bothered by a true ethical problem, which is how could SS officers and soldiers do their dirty job?
信息是 你面对的是 我是说 某种意义上 希姆莱 那是它的恐怖之处 这是一个真正的困扰的伦理问题 那就是党卫军军官和士兵如何做他们的肮脏工作
slaughtering, killing children, women, without becoming beasts themselves.
屠杀 杀害儿童、妇女 而不使自己变成野兽
His solution was this kind of heroism, that you perceive your very evil acts as the supreme act of heroism, ready to descend into this hell for the good of the people.
他的解决方案是这种英雄主义 即你将自己非常邪恶的行为视为英雄主义的至高行为 愿意为了人民的利益 而下降到这个地狱
It's a terrifying logic.
这是一种恐怖的逻辑
So since, unfortunately, time is running, let me go on.
所以既然不幸地 时间在流逝 让我继续
This delicate relationship between what we believe and what we know, or rather, what we explicitly know and this disavowed beliefs, they are at work in a very refined way in our daily experience.
我们所相信的与我们所知道的 或者更确切地说 我们明确知道的与所否认的信仰之间的这种微妙关系 它们在我们的日常经验中以非常精致的方式发挥着作用
Often you believe in something, you can even believe sincerely, but nonetheless it's It's a great shock and surprise if you see your belief confirmed directly in a too brutal way.
很多时候你相信某件事 你甚至可以真诚地相信 但尽管如此 如果你的信仰以一种太过直接和残酷的方式被证实 通常会是一个巨大的冲击和惊讶
Did you see the film, isn't there, I was told that tomorrow there will be here a play by Steve Martin, somewhere, okay, doesn't matter, performed.
你看过那部电影吗 我被告知明天这里将上演史蒂夫·马丁的一部戏剧 将会上演
The point is that he acts in a film, Leap of Faith from 1992, maybe you saw it, which This is one thing about a con artist, this preacher who treats, he heals, cripples, but it's all a stage.
重点是他在1992年的电影《天降神迹》中扮演的角色 你可能看过 这是关于一个骗子传教士 他治疗、治愈残疾人 但这一切都是一场表演
Then once, he does something which he thinks it's treating, but it's a true miracle.
然后有一次 他做了一些他认为是治疗的事情 但那是一个真正的奇迹
He totally breaks down.
他彻底崩溃了
It's a shock.
这是一个冲击
So things are here much more refined, in the sense that, what does it mean to believe?
所以事情在这里更为精细 意味着 相信是什么意思
Often, people who believe, believe with a distance.
经常 相信的人是带着一定距离相信的
I often notice how religious people often pray and obey the ritual, not as Pascal thought, in order to really believe.
我经常注意到宗教信徒经常祈祷和遵守仪式 不是像帕斯卡想的 为了真正地相信
You know that advice of Blaise Pascal to unbelievers who want to believe.
你知道布莱斯·帕斯卡（Blaise Pascal）对那些想要相信的无信者的建议
You don't believe, here it is what you should do. Simply act as if you believe.
你不信 而你应该做的是 只要表现得好像你相信一样
obey the ritual, kneel down, pray, do good works, and belief will come by itself.
遵循仪式 跪下 祈祷 做好事 信仰将自然而然来临
I claim, unfortunately, that often it's the exact opposite.
我认为 不幸的是 通常情况恰恰相反
It's that what if you really believe, but in a too intense way, it's horrible directly to believe?
就是如果你真的相信了 但是是以一种太过强烈的方式 直接相信是不是很可怕的
Then maybe the solution is do as if you believe, and your belief will be externalized in the ritual out there.
那么也许解决方案是做得好像你相信一样 你的信仰将在外面的仪式中体现
You no longer will directly have to believe.
你将不再需要直接相信
Now let's move to more problematic topic.
现在让我们转向更具问题性的话题
This gap between what we rationally know and what we unconsciously believe tells us, I claim, a lot about our predicament, namely how we relate usually to the prospect of ecological catastrophe.
我们理性所知与我们潜意识中的信仰之间的这一差距 我认为 很多地告诉了我们我们的困境 即我们通常如何看待生态灾难的前景
This is a paradox.
这是一个悖论
Basically, we know catastrophe is coming.
基本上 我们知道灾难即将到来
there will be global warming, whatever.
会有全球变暖 等等
But why don't we act?
但我们为什么不采取行动
Why don't we do something?
我们为什么不做点什么
I don't think it's enough, this simple leftist explanation, yes, big companies, manipulation, whatever.
我认为 这种简单的左派解释是不够的 是的 大公司、操纵等等
I claim we know, but we don't believe.
我认为我们知道 但我们不相信
That is to say, imagine yourself reading a report on global warming, horrible this, that.
也就是说 想象一下你自己在阅读一份关于全球变暖的报告 可怕的这个、那个
But then you go out, you see sun, trees, grass.
但然后你走出去 你看到阳光、树木、草地
My god, you say, but this cannot really disappear.
我的天哪 你说 但这些不可能真的消失
That's the tragedy, that what prevents us from taking seriously the prospect of ecological catastrophe. It's precisely our direct immersion into our life world.
这就是悲剧 阻止我们认真对待生态灾难前景的正是我们直接沉浸于我们的生活世界
These are beliefs which are part of the way we act in reality.
这些信仰是我们在现实中行动方式的一部分
And it's extremely difficult to renounce them.
放弃它们极其困难
There is a very important theoretical consequence to be drawn from this paradoxical one.
从这种悖论中可以得出一个非常重要的理论后果
You know the usual criticism of why we are in ecological deadlock.
你知道通常对我们为何陷入生态僵局的批评
The idea is the following one.
观点如下
We trust too much science, abstract scientific reasoning.
我们过分信赖科学、抽象的科学推理
We should not forget that science is secondary.
我们不应忘记科学是次要的
It's alienated secondary product of our primordial attitude which is our being embedded in a concrete life world.
这是我们原初态度的疏离性的次生产物 而我们的原初态度是我们存在于具体生活世界中的体现
You see, you feel, you sense with the earth where you live, and so on.
你看到、你感觉到、你用你所居住的地球来感知 等等
But I claim that that's not enough.
但我认为那还不够
We cannot return to this immediate life world experience, because this exactly is the problem.
我们无法回到直接的生活世界经验 因为这正是问题所在
If we are to confront properly, I claim, ecological catastrophe,
我认为 如果我们要正确地面对生态灾难
we have to confront, we have to outgrow precisely this direct embeddedness.
我们必须面对 我们必须超越这种直接的根植性
Now let's go on.
现在让我们继续
I hope it will be a little bit more amusing what I say now.
我希望我现在说的会有点更有趣
Namely, how, then, do we relate towards this?
也就是说 那么 我们如何看待这一点呢
Where do we detect this gap in our beliefs or knowledge, this inconsistency?
我们在哪里发现我们的信仰或知识中的这种差距、这种不一致
I know it's true, but nonetheless, I don't believe it.
我知道这是真的 但尽管如此 我不相信它
Let me make a simple observation.
让我做一个简单的观察
Did you notice how every normative order, in the sense of rules that we obey, in order to be members of certain collective,
你有没有注意到 每一种规范秩序 意即我们为了成为某个集体的成员而遵守的规则
from family to whenever you want, is never a simple set of rules that you learn them you are in.
从家庭到任何你想要的地方 从来都不是一套你学会了就能加入的简单规则
What's so interesting is that there are never simply only rules.
有趣的是 永远不仅仅只有规则
There are always rules and then meta rules.
总是有规则 然后是元规则
That is to say, rules which tell you how to relate to these rules, to take them seriously or not, how seriously.
也就是说 告诉你如何对待这些规则 是否认真对待它们 以及认真到何种程度的规则
For example, it's often that there is a prohibition.
例如 通常存在一种禁令
You shouldn't do it.
你不应该这么做
But we all know that it usually means, in many cases, do it discreetly.
但我们都知道 这在许多情况下通常意味着 要做就要谨慎地做
Or sometimes, especially with some kind of sexual prohibitions, it's even a direct solicitation, do it or whatever.
或者有时 特别是对于某些性禁忌 它甚至是一种直接的诱惑 请做或其他什么
So then can be prohibitions which are not meant to be taken seriously.
所以 可能存在一些并不是要被认真对待的禁令
If you take them seriously, you appear an idiot, how should I put it.
如果你认真对待它们 你会显得像个傻瓜 我该怎么说
Like, you are here a little bit different.
像 你在这里有点不同
You take your state seriously.
你认真对待你的国家
For example, this is my legacy from the socialist regime in my country, no?
例如 这是我国家社会主义制度留给我的遗产 不是吗
Like, if I try not to pay taxes to find a loophole, and if somebody tells me, how can you?
像 如果我试图不交税 找到一个漏洞 如果有人告诉我 你怎么能这样
We have to pay taxes all.
我们都必须交税
I mean, the guy is an idiot.
我的意思是 那个家伙是个傻瓜
You know what I mean?
你知道我的意思吗
OK.
好的
But there is something much more interesting here.
但这里有更有趣的东西
the opposite paradox.
相反的悖论
The paradox not of prohibition which between the lines tells you do it, do it discreetly, whatever, but do it, but an offer of freedom.
字里行间的悖论不是禁止 而是告诉你要这样做 谨慎地做 无论如何 而是这样做 而是提供这样的自由
You are permitted something, but on condition that you don't use this option.
您被允许执行某些操作 但条件是您不使用此选项
As if you can do it, you are given the freedom to do it on condition that you will not do it.
就好像你能做一样 你被给予了做它的自由 但前提是你不会去做
Again, there are especially, for example, in different political regimes.
特别是在不同的政治制度中
You have freedom to choose on condition that you make the right choice, that's the truth.
你有选择的自由 但前提是你做出正确的选择 这才是真相
Or even in our daily lives.
甚至在我们的日常生活中
For example, recently a friend from Japan told me, do you know that in Japan workers have the right to 40 days holiday every year?
例如 最近一个来自日本的朋友告诉我 你知道在日本工人每年有40天的假期权利吗
But you are expected not to use this right in its full extent.
但你被期望不要完全使用这个权利
The implicit rule is not more than 20 days.
隐含的规则是不超过20天
Then I asked them, OK, but then don't you simply write 20 days.
然后我问他们 那为什么你们不直接写20天呢
He told me, you are an idiot.
他告诉我 你是个傻瓜
You don't get it.
你不懂
And he was right.
他是对的
I didn't get it.
我没明白
Why not?
为什么不明白
It's the same as, do you know, this is always what fascinated me, because I think this is communication between people at its most mysterious and elementary, these empty gestures.
就像 你知道 这总是让我着迷的地方 因为我认为这是人与人之间最神秘、最基本的交流 那些空洞的手势
You are offered something, but you shouldn't use it.
有人给你提供了什么 但你不应该使用它
For example, all of you probably were already in this situation.
例如 你们中的许多人可能已经遇到过这种情况
you were invited by somebody older, richer, to dinner.
你被某个年纪更大、更富有的人邀请去吃晚饭
Now, you knew it was absolutely clear in advance that he will pay.
现在 你知道很明显他会付账
But isn't it kind of a ritual of politeness that you have to insist for some time, no, no, let me pay.
但这不就是一种礼貌的仪式吗 你必须坚持一段时间 不不 让我来付
Just don't do, by the way, what I did once I insisted too long.
顺便说一句 别像我之前那样坚持太久
And then the guy said, if you won't, do it.
然后那人说 如果你不肯的话 那就你付吧
Then I have to stage all this comedy off.
然后我开始像表演喜剧一样开始胡编乱走
Oh my god, I forgot my credit cards or whatever.
哦我的天啊 我忘了带信用卡之类的
But there are other beautiful examples.
但还有其他美丽的例子
For example, she is my friend, although we fight all the time theoretically, personally she is my friend, Judith Butler.
例如 她是我的朋友 虽然在理论方面 我们一直在吵架 但就我个人而言 她是我的朋友 朱迪思·巴特勒
Recently I met her in Switzerland and I was not too rude to her, but I used some degenerate grip, whatever, I'm horrible when I eat.
最近我在瑞士遇见了她 我对她并没有太粗鲁 但我用了一些堕落的握法 无论如何 我吃饭的时候很糟糕
So I saw that I did hurt her.
所以我看到我确实伤害了她
So I felt bad afterwards.
所以事后我感到不好
I phoned her.
我给她打了电话
I told her, sorry, blah, blah.
我告诉她 对不起 等等
And then she told me, thanks, I appreciate it.
然后她告诉我 谢谢 我很感激
But really, I wasn't offended.
但实际上 我没有被冒犯
I knew you didn't mean it.
我知道你不是那个意思
You owe me no apology.
你不欠我任何道歉
She was absolutely sincere.
她是绝对真诚的
And I was really grateful.
我真的很感激
But you see, the paradox is that it was possible for her to say, you owe me no apology, only after I did apologize.
但你看 矛盾在于 只有在我道歉之后 她才可能说 你不欠我道歉
And this is not hypocrisy.
这不是伪善
That's the mystery of communication.
这是沟通的神秘之处
You do something, the result is nothing.
你做了一些事 结果是“无”
You do something which is declared superfluous.
你做了一些被认为是多余的事情
But in order to be declared superfluous, you have to do it.
但为了被宣称为多余 你就必须这样做
This is how now you will say, what's the profit?
这就是现在你会问的 这有什么有利的么
The profit is respect, friendship, love, communication, through communication, through communication between us.
有利的是尊重、友谊、爱、沟通 通过沟通 通过我们之间的沟通
I don't know.
我不知道
My favourite example even here is we have this ritual in my country, let us say that
我最喜欢的例子甚至在这里 我们国家有这样一个仪式 比方说
I and a friend of mine compete for the same job.
我和我的一个朋友争夺同一份工作
Let us say he wins, I lose.
比方说他赢了 我输了
It's a ritual in my country that then the winner should say to the loser, listen, I know that you deserved it more, why don't I step down and you will get the job.
我国的一个仪式是 然后胜利者应该对失败者说 听着 我知道你更应该得到它 我应该退出 你应该得到这份工作
But of course you have to say no, no, no, you can have it.
但当然你必须说 不不不 你可以拥有它
What's the profit?
有利的是什么
the friendship is saved in this way, frankly, no?
这样的话 友谊得以保存 坦白说 不是吗
So what I'm saying here is that the most delicate texture of our human relations moves, operates at this level,
所以我在这里所说的是 我们人际关系中最微妙的结构在这个层面上移动、运作 不是在明确的规则层面上
at the level not of explicit rules but of this between the lines rules, you know, like I give you an offer but these meta rules tell me it's an offer to be rejected or whatever.
而是在字里行间的规则层面上 你知道 就像我给你一个报价 但这些元规则告诉我这是一个被拒绝的提议或其他什么
And now I come to the concluding point, if you allow me a little bit of time.
现在我要讲到结论了 如果你允许我一点时间的话
It is that I claim that what is going on today, what worries me, is that these unspoken rules,
我想说的是 现在发生的、让我担心的是这些潜规则
what I would call following Hegel, the ethical substance of our being, this I claim is slowly surely, if you want, is disintegrating today.
我所说的追随黑格尔的东西 我们存在的道德实质 我认为 它现在肯定在慢慢瓦解
There are some profound changes operating at that level.
在这个层面上正在发生一些深刻的变化
What do you mean by this?
你这是什么意思
Let me take a book which I, as an atheist, should like, but I'm not.
让我拿一本书来说 作为一个无神论者 我应该喜欢 但我不是
I think it's a horrible book.
我认为这是一本可怕的书
It was a big New York Times bestseller around a year ago,
大约一年前 这是《纽约时报》的畅销书
Sam Harris, The End of Belief.
萨姆·哈里斯 《信仰的终结》
It tells all the title.
标题就说明了一切
The thesis of the book is our, and he It means specifically our religions of the book, Jewish, Christian, Muslim, and so on.
这本书的论点是 我们的 他特别指的是我们的这些宗教 犹太教、基督教、伊斯兰教等等
Beliefs are ridiculously out of date.
信念已经过时得可笑了
They belong to a totally different epoch.
它们属于一个完全不同的时代
Today, they only cause ethnic slaughter and so on.
如今 它们只会导致种族屠杀等问题
So we have to outgrow them.
所以我们必须超越它们
And all he allows is some kind of a vague Buddhist, whatever, oriental meditation with no epistemological commitment.
他所允许的仅仅是某种模糊的佛教禅修 或者其他没有认识论承诺的东方冥想
But I think there is something significant here, that precisely the guy who claims this, the end of belief,
但我认为这里有一点很重要 那就是正是声称这一点的人 信仰的终结
is also the guy who advocates the use of torture in this book.
也是在这本书中提倡使用酷刑的人
And it's interesting to take a look at how does he justify torture.
看看他如何为酷刑辩护是很有趣的
Because the point is to find exactly what is wrong in his reasoning.
因为重点是找出他的推理中到底哪里出了问题
His reasoning is very simple, basically.
他的推理基本上很简单
He starts with this problem.
他从这个问题开始
Why is it that most of us find it more problematic, much more problematic, to torture somebody in front of us than to push a button which will kill hundreds of thousand people out there, out of our sight?
为什么我们大多数人发现 在我们面前折磨某人比按下一个按钮杀死在我们看不见的地方的成千上万的人更加难以接受
He claims he calls this the moon illusion, in parallel with this old perceptual illusion.
他声称这叫做月亮错觉 类似于那种老的感知错觉
If you don't know how it is, you think the moon is just a small object out there in the sky.
如果你不知道这是什么 你会认为月亮只是天空中的一个小物体
But he said, in the same way that we know now rationally that moon is a quite large object,
但他说 就像我们现在理性地知道月亮实际上是一个相当大的物体
that we should do the same restructuring of our ethical experience.
我们应该对我们的伦理经验进行同样的重构
So for him, it's a pretty horrifying conclusion.
所以对他来说 这是一个相当恐怖的结论
The fact that we cannot torture, most of us at least,
我们大多数人至少不能面对面地折磨某人
somebody face to face is simply, I quote him,
简而言之 我引用他的话
the reason for this inability to torture another person is every bit as neurological as those that give rise to the moon illusion.
这种无法折磨另一个人的原因与那些导致月亮错觉的原因一样 完全是神经学上的
So simply, let's grow up.
所以简单来说 让我们成熟起来
Let's learn to put things in proper proportion.
让我们学会正确地对待事物
And following a ruthless utilitarian calculation,
遵循一种无情的功利主义计算
let's become aware that it's even your duty, as he puts it, to torture somebody in front of you if in this way you can prevent much larger suffering.
让我们意识到 正如他所说 如果通过这种方式你可以防止更大的痛苦 那么在你面前折磨某人甚至是你的责任
Now, Harris concedes that, nonetheless, we cannot simply outgrow our deeply ingrained habits.
现在 哈里斯承认 尽管如此 我们不能简单地超越我们根深蒂固的习惯
So he proposed something which I think is even more tasteless, a kind of a truth pill.
所以他提出了一个我认为更加无味的建议 一种真相药丸
Here is how he says, a drug that would deliver both the instrument of torture and the instrument of its utter concealment.
他是这么说的 一种药物 既是酷刑的工具 也是完全隐蔽的
The action of the pill, OK, I will cut it short.
药丸的作用 好吧 我就简短说吧
The idea is a pill which causes indescribable suffering, but not visible from the outside.
这个想法是 有一种药丸 会造成难以描述的痛苦 但从外部看不出来
You have a terrorist.
现在有一个恐怖分子
You, instead of torturing him there, which would make you feel bad, you give him the pill.
你不会肉体上折磨他 这会让你感到难受 那么你给他吃这个药丸
And the terrorist, suspected terrorist, just seems to take a half an hour nap.
这个恐怖分子 怀疑中的恐怖分子 只是似乎小睡了半个小时
But then he awakens.
但然后他醒来了
And I confess everything you want, no?
我会坦白你想知道的一切 不是吗
The first thing that bothers me here is that how this fits perfectly our postmodern logic of,
我在这里首先困扰的是 这是如何完美契合我们后现代的逻辑
which I develop in many of the books, of decaf coffee.
我在许多书中发展的 脱咖啡因咖啡的逻辑
We like today's projects, sorry, objects, products,
我们今天喜欢的项目 对不起 商品
without paying the price for them.
不付出代价就想拥有
Coffee, but decaf coffee.
咖啡 但是脱咖啡因的咖啡
Beer, but beer without alcohol.
啤酒 但是无酒精啤酒
A cake, but fat-free cake.
蛋糕 但是无脂肪蛋糕
And don't you think that this is only for products?
别以为这只适用于产品
I claim it's exactly the same in our intersubjective relations.
我认为这在我们的人际关系中完全一样
Colin Powell's theory of war was precisely decaffeinated war.
科林·鲍威尔的战争理论正是脱咖啡因的战争
war, but no victims on our side.
战争 但我们这边没有受害者
And to be a little bit more nasty,
稍微有点刻薄地说
I would say that at least the way it is in its predominant form, multiculturalist tolerance is the tolerance of, to be nasty, the decaffeinated other.
我会说 至少以它的主要形式 多元文化主义的容忍是对脱咖啡因的他者的容忍
No?
不是吗
The other is abstracted.
另一个是被抽象化的
For example, I think this is the filthiest form of racism to celebrate Native Americans, if you call them that.
比如 我认为庆祝所谓的“美洲原住民”是最肮脏的种族主义形式
I found this disgusting, even more racist than Indians, because I spoke with one of them, and he told me, Native Americans, what is this?
我发现这非常令人厌恶 甚至比对待印第安人还要种族主义 因为我与他们中的一个人交谈过 他问我 “美洲原住民”是什么意思
Are we part of nature?
我们是自然的一部分吗
What are you, cultural Americans?
你们是什么 文化美国人吗
And he said, to be called an Indian, at least then my name is a monument to white men's stupidity.
他说 被称为印第安人 至少我的名字是白人愚蠢的纪念碑
No, like, they thought better.
不 就像 他们以为更好
They thought they are in India, no?
他们以为自己在印度 不是吗
But did you notice how these politically great guys,
但你有没有注意到 这些政治上伟大的家伙
if you hear them talk about Native Americans, it's, you know, people who live in a holistic way, harmony with nature, have their dances spiritually connected to Earth, nothing about torture, family rapes, whatever.
如果你听他们谈论美洲原住民 就会知道 那些与自然和谐共生、通过舞蹈与大地精神连接的人们 却对折磨、家庭强奸等一无所知
And I don't say this in, I think, so what I want to say is that this is for me, this cleansing of the other is the most racist thing.
我不是这样说的 我想说的是 对我而言 这种对他者的净化是最种族主义的事情
So back to this, this is the first problem I have with Sam Harris.
所以回到这个问题 这是我对萨姆·哈里斯的第一个问题
The second problem, but it's just a minor remark, is that, fine, so we are following KGB.
第二个问题 不过这只是一个小备注 那就是 好吧 所以我们在追随克格勃
Namely, I learned in a book about the misuses of psychiatry in Soviet Union that they already had it.
也就是说 我在一本关于苏联精神病学滥用的书中了解到 他们早就有了这种方法
The standard way to torture dissidents there was under the mask up, because there in Soviet Union in the last decades, dissidents being critical of the system
在苏联的最后几十年里 折磨持不同政见者的标准方式是在掩饰之下进行的 因为在苏联
was defined as a special form of social schizophrenia or whatever, no megalomania that you can create.
持批判性看法的人被定义为一种特殊形式的社会精神分裂症或什么样的妄想症 你可以创造这些名词
They injected something here in the region of your heart, and it was a terrifying experience.
他们在你心脏区域注射了某种东西 那是一种恐怖的体验
It slowed down your heartbeat.
它减慢了你的心跳
You thought, like, you know, you are slowly dying.
你会觉得 你知道 你正在慢慢死去
From the outside, you just took a nap.
从外面看 你只是小睡了一会
It's exactly what Sam Harris described.
这正是萨姆·哈里斯所描述的
From the inside, it was a nightmare.
从内心来看 那是一场噩梦
But, but, now I come to the truly central point.
但 但 现在我要谈到真正的核心问题
Nonetheless, you will say, but what's the point?
尽管如此 你会说 但问题是什么呢
What is fundamentally wrong with Harris?
哈里斯的根本错误是什么
Here we come to the topic of what in Judeo-Christian tradition, and Freud also refers to this tradition in his theory of how we relate to others, we call the neighbor.
这里我们谈到了在犹太-基督教传统中的一个主题 弗洛伊德在他的理论中也提到了这一传统 即我们如何与他人相处 我们称之为邻居
The neighbor is something very radical in Judeo-Christian tradition.
邻居在犹太-基督教传统中是一个非常激进的概念
The neighbor is not the other who is like us.
邻居并不是像我们一样的其他人
The neighbor is some kind of a traumatic presence.
邻居是某种创伤性的存在
It's the other person, if you want, in the abyss of its infinity.
如果你愿意的话 那就是在无限深渊中的另一个人
And there is always something monstrous about it.
并且总有一些怪物般的东西
But the name of that monstrosity is freedom, no?
但那种怪物的名字是自由 不是吗
You cannot ever be sure you promised me this, but how do I know?
你永远无法确定你向我承诺过这一点 但我怎么知道呢
How do I know that I can trust you, and so on?
我怎么知道我能信任你 等等
Which is why we need promises with people which are not neighbors.
这就是为什么我们需要与非邻居做出承诺
If I were to know you totally, in a kind of a cognitivist or brain sciences dream, that I know the mechanisms, how you decide, I wouldn't need promises.
如果我能完全了解你 就像是在一种认知主义或大脑科学的梦境中 我知道你做决定的机制 那么我就不需要承诺了
Promises are here because precisely I don't know what an abyss you are.
承诺之所以存在 正是因为我不知道你是什么样的深渊
And I think we should be very careful here not to, how should I put it, not to idealize the notion of the neighbor.
我认为我们在这里应该非常小心 不应该理想化邻居的概念
There is something irreducibly traumatic in the notion of the neighbor, which is why a little lesson in theology.
邻居的概念中有一些不可减少的创伤性 这就是为什么需要一点神学课
If you look already at the Old Testament, I claim that the true function of the 10 commandments
如果你看旧约 我认为十诫的真正功能 不仅仅是让你爱你的邻居 而且还要保持适当的距离
It can be very unpleasant, intrusive to come too close to it.
靠得太近可能非常不愉快 具有侵扰性
Why?
为什么
Let me give you a simple example.
让我给你一个简单的例子
I hope you were, but it's not as loving as it may appear.
我希望你是 但它并不像看起来那么有爱
You were, some of you at least, I hope most of you all, in a situation where somebody declared intense love to you.
你们中的一些人 至少我希望你们大多数人 都经历过某人向你表达强烈的爱
approaches you and you see that it's sincere, it's not a joke, you are the center of my life, I totally love you,
接近你 并且你看得出这是真诚的 不是开玩笑 你是我生命的中心 我完全爱你
admit it if you are honest that maybe you enjoyed it but for a split of a second at least you were horrified.
如果你诚实地承认 也许你享受了这一刻 但至少一瞬间你感到恐惧
I mean it's something horrifying to be in such an intense way the focus of all desires of another person, which is why, do you know that William Butler Yeats famous poem like
我的意思是 成为另一个人所有欲望的焦点是一种可怕的事情 这就是为什么 你知道那首威廉·巴特勒·叶芝的著名诗歌吗
You walk, be careful how you walk because you are walking in my dreams.
你走路要小心 因为你在我梦中行走
It's horrible to be somebody who as a real person walks in a dream of dreams of another person.
成为一个在另一个人的梦中行走的真实人物是一种可怕的经历
It's a very claustrophobic experience.
这是一种非常令人窒息的体验
So again, this topic of neighbor is crucial, abyssal topic.
所以再说一遍 邻居这个话题是关键 是一个深渊话题
I even claim that we are basically, Our basic fear is fear of the neighbor.
我甚至声称 我们基本的恐惧是对邻居的恐惧
And all racisms play upon this, this abyss of the other.
所有种族主义都是基于对他者这个深渊的恐惧
And that's, incidentally, one of the sad things, for me at least, going on today, namely the fact of how,
而且 顺便说一句 对我来说至少 今天发生的一件悲哀的事情 即如何
did you notice how in the last two, three decades, our politics is defined by two, three features?
你有没有注意到 在过去的二三十年里 我们的政治是由二三个特点定义的
One is that the only way to mobilize people, not just to do this technocratic administration, but to mobilize people passionately, is to play on a fear.
一个是 动员人们的唯一方法 不仅仅是进行技术官僚管理 而是热情地动员人们 就是利用恐惧
The only politics of passions today is a politics of fear.
今天唯一的激情政治是恐惧政治
And unfortunately, not only for the right, also for the left,
不幸的是 不仅仅是对右派 也对左派
fear of immigrants, fear of, I don't know, fear of ecological catastrophe, fear of the state high taxes, whatever you want, fear of sexual depravity, and so on.
恐惧移民 恐惧生态灾难 恐惧国家高税 无论你想要什么 恐惧性道德败坏等等
I claim what is beneath this is effectively fear of the neighbor.
我声称 这背后实际上是对邻居的恐惧
Another thing to be noted here is how sad thing about today is then how do we deal with the neighbor?
这里要注意的另一件事是 今天多么令人悲伤的是 我们如何与邻居打交道
You cannot simply swallow him or her.
你不能简单地吞噬他或她
Neighbor is out there in its abyss, which is why, again, I claim that this notion of love thy neighbor, it's something very radical.
邻居就在它的深渊里 这就是为什么我再次声称这种爱邻居的观念是非常激进的
It means love thy neighbor, love this radical otherness.
它意味着爱你的邻居 爱这种彻底的差异
Not just love somebody who is like me.
不只是爱像自己那样的人
It's that today, the way we deal with it is tolerance.
今天 我们处理它的方式是宽容
And here, I'm sorry, I don't have time.
在这里 对不起 我没有时间
Maybe tomorrow morning at the restraint seminar,
也许明天早上在约束研讨会上
I want to go with it because I'm now in intense dialogue with that wonderful book.
我想继续讨论 因为我现在正在与那本精彩的书进行激烈的对话
but I have my critical with Wendy Brown's book on regulating aversion.
但我对温迪·布朗关于调节厌恶的书持批评态度
She draws, nonetheless, wonderful conclusions and asks the right questions.
尽管如此 她得出了精彩的结论并提出了正确的问题
Namely, the basic problem is the following one.
即 基本问题是以下这个
Why is the category of tolerance universalized to such an extent today?
为什么今天宽容的范畴被普遍化到如此程度
Did you notice how problems which 20, 30, 40 years ago were perceived not as problem of intolerance, but problems of injustice, inequality, and so on, are today rephrased as problems of tolerance.
你有没有注意到 20、30、40年前被视为不公正、不平等等问题的问题 今天被重新表述为宽容的问题
Racism is today, you don't tolerate my way of life, whatever, but make a stupid experiment, the moment of glory of United States Martin Luther King, the fight for racial equality.
种族主义今天是 你不宽容我的生活方式 无论如何 但做一个愚蠢的实验 美国的荣耀时刻马丁·路德·金 为种族平等而战
I made a simple experiment, go to internet, put some of his speeches, and put tolerance in tolerance, practically absent.
我做了一个简单的实验 上网 放上他的一些演讲 在演讲中搜索宽容不宽容 几乎不存在
Martin Luther King didn't fight for tolerance.
马丁·路德·金并非为宽容而战
He fought for end of exploitation, end of injustice, inequality.
他为结束剥削、结束不公正、不平等而战
That was the problem for him.
那是他的问题所在
I mean, it would be even obscene and racist to say for him, oh, we blacks want whites to tolerate us.
我的意思是 即使是说对他来说 哦 我们黑人希望白人宽容、容忍我们 也会是一种亵渎和种族主义的说法
You know, it's the same ridicule as to say, as if a eminist would have said, we want men to tolerate women.
你知道 这就像是说 好像一位女权主义者会说 我们希望男人容忍女人一样荒谬
Which is even a very obscene idea, like many of my male friends would have said,
这甚至是一个非常亵渎的想法 就像我的许多男性朋友会说
I can somehow grant equality to women, but tolerate them never there.
我可以以某种方式给予女性平等 但永远不会容忍她们
So OK, that's another story.
所以好吧 那是另一个故事
What's underlying this is something that should be called culturalization of politics.
这背后的是一种应该被称为政治文化化的东西
In our postmodern era, where economy is more and more reduced to something that experts do, just administration.
在我们的后现代时代 经济越来越多地被简化为专家们所做的事情 仅仅是行政管理
The only conflicts that remain are perceived as conflicts of culture.
剩下的唯一冲突被视为文化冲突
But now, really, sorry to conclude, this notion of neighbor is something terrifying, I claim.
但现在 真的 抱歉要这么总结 我声称这个邻居的概念是某种恐怖的东西
In what sense?
在什么意义上呢
In the sense that, again, neighbor is not the wealth of another person, as we put it, his or her inner life, what I see in you.
在这个意义上 再次强调 邻居并不是另一个人的财富 正如我们所说的 他或她的内心世界 我在你身上所看到的（是一份给予我的财富）
No, this level is usually a lie.
不 这个层面通常是谎言
There is a wonderful poetic, but I totally reject it.
它有一种精彩的诗意 但我完全拒绝它
Multicultural phrase, which is something like this.
多元文化的说法 大概是这样的
It's supposed to be a deep insight.
它被认为是一种深刻的洞察
I think it's precisely pseudo-depth.
我认为这正是伪深度
It's an enemy is someone whose story you have not heard.
敌人是你没有听过他的故事的人
It sounds so noble, you know, like you are my enemy if I just objectivize you, you there.
这听起来很高尚 你知道 就像如果我只是将你客观化 你在那里 你就是我的敌人
But oh, if I take care or make the effort of understanding you from within, oh, then I will see that you have your standpoint.
但哦 如果我关心或努力从内部理解你 哦 那么我会看到你有你的立场
OK, up to a certain level, this is undoubtedly true.
好吧 在一定程度上 这无疑是真的
But I claim only up to a certain level.
但我声称只到一定程度
And the limits are clear if I simply paraphrase this or apply to a very specific case.
如果我简单地改述这个或将其应用到一个非常具体的情况 限制就很清楚了
Would you also be ready to say Hitler was our enemy because we didn't hear his story?
你也会愿意说希特勒是我们的敌人 因为我们没有听他的故事吗
I did hear his story.
我听过他的故事
I read Mein Kampf and so on.
我读过《我的奋斗》等等
And what shocks me is how no matter how horrible your politics is, you always can find a nice way, as we usually put it, to rationalize it, to tell yourself a story about it.
让我震惊的是 无论你的政治有多恶劣 你总能找到一种好的方式 正如我们通常所说 对它进行合理化 给自己讲一个关于它的故事
So the radical conclusion here is that, and I think this is another deepest insight of Judeo-Christian tradition,
所以这里的激进结论是 我认为这是犹太-基督教传统的另一个最深刻的洞察
is that the ultimate truth, the truth of you as a unique person, where you really stand,
那就是你作为一个独特个体的终极真理 你真正站立的地方
is not when you go deep into yourself and the deepest sincere self-identification or whatever.
不是当你深入自己内心 进行最深的真诚自我认同或其他什么
At that level, we usually lie.
在那个层面 我们通常是在撒谎
That's not the ultimate truth.
那不是终极真理
Which is why, if you want to get this point, I advise you to read two books.
这就是为什么 如果你想理解这一点 我建议你阅读两本书
One is Aldous Huxley, the English guy, gray eminence.
一本是阿尔杜斯·赫胥黎的《灰色权威》 那个英国人
It's the story of Father Joseph, Per Joseph, the foreign minister of Cardinal Richelieu in the early 17th century, the 30 years' war.
这是关于约瑟夫神父的故事 他是17世纪早期 三十年战争期间 黎塞留枢机主教的外交大臣
What's so fascinating in this person?
这个人有什么吸引人的地方
He was, for that epoch, evil incarnated.
对那个时代来说 他是邪恶的化身
The worst realpolitik manipulator, he concluded a pact between Catholic France and Protestant Sweden against Catholic Austria to prevent unification of Germany.
最糟糕的现实政治操纵者 他在天主教法国和新教瑞典之间缔结了协议 对抗天主教奥地利 以阻止德国统一
So we can even say he's guilty for Hitler in a certain way.
所以我们甚至可以说 从某种意义上讲 他对希特勒有责任
Because it was because of his political plotting that German was not unified earlier as a nation state.
因为正是由于他的政治阴谋 德国没有在早些时候作为一个民族国家而统一
We all know this is what caused First World War and so on.
我们都知道 这是导致第一次世界大战等的原因
Now, what is the shock?
现在 什么是令人震惊的
The shock is that the same person ordering tortures, poisoning, blah, was, in the evening, after his work was done, was writing the most precious of incredible depth mystical meditations.
令人震惊的是 同一个人下令施行酷刑、毒害等等 在晚上 在他的工作完成后 他正在写最珍贵的、令人难以置信的深度神秘冥想
Absolutely, how should I put it in a vulgar way, top level, at the level of Santa Teresa, whoever you want.
他绝对地 用俗语说 是顶级水平 达到圣特蕾莎或任何你想要的水平
And this is what bothered Huxley.
这就是令赫胥黎困扰的问题
I think his solution is wrong, but this gap.
我认为他的解决方案是错误的 但这个差距
The same, Let's Go to the East, a simple book by Brian Victoria, Zen at War.
同样 《让我们前往东方》 布莱恩·维多利亚的一本简单的书 《战争中的禅》
The same problem.
同样的问题
We have undoubtedly authentic Zen Buddhist monks, like the one who was very popular.
我们有无疑是真正的禅宗佛教僧侣 像那个在60年代很受嬉皮士欢迎的铃木大拙
If some of you are old enough, in the 60s era, hippies, DT Suzuki, the great.
如果你们中的一些人年龄足够大 会记得
Yeah, but he was in the 30s, 40s.
是的 但他是在30年代、40年代
He was not only totally supporting Japanese militarism, but even was writing justification of it,
他不仅完全支持日本的军国主义 甚至还为它辩护
claiming that for the majority of people, this unconditional obedience of military discipline, you don't think there is order.
声称对大多数人来说 这种军事纪律的无条件服从 你不需要思考命令 只需执行
You do it.
你就这么做
It's the only way to satori, to enlightenment, to overcoming of your force.
这是通往悟道、通往启蒙、克服你的力量的唯一方式
So the same paradox.
所以同样的悖论
And I think the lesson of it is very clear that when we who stand in a Christian tradition, when we speak about redemption, blah, blah, all this,
我认为这其中的教训非常清楚 当我们这些站在基督教传统中的人谈论救赎等等时
is something totally different than this gnostic or pagan perspective of going deep into yourself,
这与那种深入自我内部的诺斯底或异教视角完全不同
finding this inner truth about yourself, and so on and so on.
找到关于自己的这种内在真理等等
Precisely, this level of inner truth is a lie.
正是这个内在真理的层面是谎言
It's the point of lying.
这是撒谎的要点
So now, believe me or not, but I will really conclude now very shortly.
所以现在 不管你信不信 但我现在真的很快就要结束了
So just two concluding points from all this.
所以从这一切中只有两点结论
Now you will tell me, OK, but this all my relativism and so on.
现在你会对我说 好吧 但这一切都是相对主义等等
We don't believe.
我们不相信
You don't know where you believe, blah, blah.
你不知道你相信什么 等等
But there are people, so-called fundamentalists, who really immediately believe.
但有些人 所谓的原教旨主义者 他们确实立即就相信了
I don't have time, it will take another hour, to develop the whole line of thought.
我没有时间 这需要另外一个小时来发展整个思路
My conclusion is they don't believe.
我的结论是他们其实不相信
Not that they are not sincere that they treat, they know.
并不是说他们对待人不真诚 他们知道
That is to say, to be very precise, I claim that belief, what bothers me in at least some type of fundamentalist, is precisely, for example, what's for me problematic in creationism as opposed to evolutionism.
也就是说 非常准确地 我认为至少某些类型的原教旨主义者让我困扰的信仰 具体来说 例如 对我来说 在创造论与进化论之间存在问题的是
It's not that it's wrong, I don't care.
不是说它是错的 我不在乎
It is that the presupposition is that you obliterate the gap between religious faith and scientific propositions and you treat religious propositions at the same level like
问题在于它们消除了宗教信仰与科学命题之间的差距 并且将宗教命题视为与科学命题同等级别的
Jesus has arisen from the dead becomes a statement like this is the DNA structure of that animal or whatsoever.
比如“耶稣从死里复活”变成了像“这是那个动物的DNA结构”之类的陈述
Which is why I think it's deeply significant that fundamentalists usually don't have any problem dealing with science.
这就是为什么我认为这一点具有深远的意义 即原教旨主义者通常在处理科学问题上没有任何问题
They love science.
他们爱科学
They all the time try to prove that there is no gap there.
他们一直试图证明那里（科学和信仰间）没有差距
You have them in Christianity, creationists.
你在基督教中有创造论者
You have them in Islam.
你在伊斯兰教中也有
You have them among the Jews.
你在犹太教中也有
For example, I learned that there is a group in Israel which takes literally the prophecy that Messiah will come when a calf will be born with totally red hair.
例如 我了解到以色列有一个团体 他们从字面上理解弥赛亚将到来的预言 即当一头全红头发的小牛出生时
So they say, let's fasten the process and they are making these biogenetic experiments to make it happen.
所以他们说 让我们加快过程 并且他们正在进行这些生物基因实验来实现它
So you know what's for me?
所以你知道对我来说是什么吗
Belief.
信仰
Belief is something different.
信仰是不同的
Belief is, for me, a kind of, there is always an element of a belief which is absurd.
对我来说 信仰总是有一种荒谬的元素
Belief is not, you don't believe in facts.
信仰并不是说 你不相信事实
To say, I believe in Christ, but fuck it, I prefer to sin or I don't take, no, you cannot.
说 我相信基督 但操它 我宁愿犯罪 或者我不接受 不 你不能
It's a belief which is by definition an existentially engaged belief.
这是一种本质上要求身心投入的信仰
It's for example, to give a pathetic example, it's ridiculous but it's true.
举一个可悲的例子 这很荒谬但却是真的
Anna Frank, if you read her memoirs, this is belief.
如果你读过安娜·弗兰克的回忆录 那就是信仰
When she writes, in spite of all the horrors that Germans are doing to us, the Jews,
当她写道 尽管德国人对我们犹太人做了所有的恐怖行为
I believe that there is a divine spark in every human being.
我相信每个人内心都有一份神圣的火花
This total counterfactual, crazy gesture.
这是一种完全违背事实、疯狂的举动
It's the same with human rights.
人权也是一样
Believing in human rights doesn't mean I look around scientifically, analyze people, I see at certain level they all have rights, then I say, oh, OK, I believe.
相信人权并不意味着我环顾四周 科学地分析人们 我看到在某种程度上他们都拥有权利 然后我说 哦 好的 我相信
No, it's a leap of faith.
不 这是一次信仰的飞跃
It's a kind of a crazy axiom.
这是一种疯狂的公理
You can be white, black, yellow, high, low, stupid.
无论你是白的、黑的、黄的、高的、矮的、愚蠢的
I posit it as a practical axiom, and this engagement is crucial.
我将其作为一个实践公理 这种投入是至关重要的
So the first paradoxical conclusion from this, I claim, is that the true danger of this kind of fundamentalism is not that it's a danger to secular knowledge, if they take over, no science.
所以 我认为从这里得出的第一个悖论结论是 这种类型的原教旨主义的真正危险不在于它对世俗知识的威胁 如果他们接管了 不再有科学
That doesn't bother me.
那并不困扰我
It's there the true end of belief.
真正的信仰结束了
It's belief at its most authentic is endangered.
最真诚的信仰是受到威胁的
So what is belief today?
那么今天的信仰是什么
Let me go briefly, no, really, three minutes.
让我简短地说 不 真的 就三分钟
You are my super ego here, yeah.
你们是我的超我 在这里 是的
Briefly back to Holocaust.
简短回到大屠杀问题
I claim that what the ultimate lesson of when I spoke about how we shouldn't play this game,
我声称 当我谈到我们不应该玩这个游戏时 大屠杀最终的教训是什么
God is the good father up there who somehow manipulates things, and you can trust on him.
即是 上帝是在上方的好父亲 他以某种方式操纵事物 你可以信任他
Everything will turn out well, and so on.
一切最终都会好转 等等
I think that with things like Holocaust, it's obscene to expect, oh, we don't know how, but mysterious are the way of the Lord.
我认为 对于像大屠杀这样的事情 期待“哦 我们不知道怎样 但上帝的道路是神秘的 它必须有一些深刻的意义 从某种角度来说是合理的 ”这是亵渎的
I claim, here I follow Shaggles reading of Christianity.
我认为 这里我跟随谢林对基督教的解读
I claim that it is what really dies on the cross.
我认为 这才是真正死在十字架上的
It's not, it's precisely this God.
确切地说是这个上帝
As Hegel would have put it, God as substance.
正如黑格尔所说的 上帝作为实体
God as this secret mind which benevolently controls everything.
上帝作为仁慈地控制一切的秘密精神
God as whatever we here do, in a kind of higher unity, everything has a secret meaning and so on and so on.
上帝作为 无论我们在这里做什么 在某种更高的统一中 一切都有一个秘密的意义 等等
Because, I mean, here we should be, if you want to be Christian, be really a Christian.
因为 我的意思是 如果你想成为一个基督徒 那就真的成为一个基督徒
That is to say, it's not that we are here, God is there, and then God from time to time, why not, he sends a messenger, okay, things turn back, come back next time, and so on.
也就是说 我们在这里 上帝在那里 然后上帝不时地 为什么不呢 他派一个使者 好的 事情回到原点 下次再来 等等
The ultimate lesson of Christianity, of embodiment, incarnation, for me is that God is engaged in our history.
基督教的终极教训 化身的教训 对我来说是 上帝参与我们的历史
What happens here on Earth, it's not something that God observes from above.
在地球上发生的事情 并不是上帝从上方观察的东西
And the way I read it is that the death of Christ on the cross, which means it's not just the death of a representative of God.
我理解的方式是 基督在十字架上的死亡 意味着这不仅仅是上帝的一个代表的死亡
And I think even we should forget all that legalistic topic.
我认为我们甚至应该忘记所有那些法律主义的话题
God paid the price for our redemption.
上帝为我们的救赎付出了代价
Oh my God.
我的天哪
Paid to whom?
付给谁
To devil?
给魔鬼
To what?
给什么
It's the death on the cross is precisely the death of that Christ of God as an absolute master which controls everything in a kind of teleological unity so that all our stains are somehow
在十字架上的死亡 恰恰是那位作为绝对主宰控制一切、在某种目的论统一中的基督的死亡
redeemed as contributing to some higher harmony, even if it's unknown to us.
以便我们所有的污点都以某种方式得到救赎 为某种更高的和谐做出贡献 即使我们不知道
God's Christ coming here suffering with us means precisely our suffering is for the real.
基督的降临在这里与我们一同受苦 恰恰意味着我们的苦难是真实的
You cannot redeem it in this stupid way.
你不能以这种愚蠢的方式赎回它
So what I claim is that something absolutely unheard of happens with Christianity, which is the death of Christ means something very radical.
所以我要说的是 基督教发生了一些绝对前所未闻的事情 基督的死亡意味着非常激进的事情
It means in all other religions we trust God, we believe in God.
它意味着 在所有其他宗教中我们信任上帝 我们相信上帝
The death of Christ means God trusted us.
而基督的死亡意味着上帝信任我们
It means like I give you your freedom, it's up to you.
这意味着就像我给你自由 这取决于你
goes for me is literally, I take it literally when it says in the Bible, whenever the two of you are there, I will be there, I am there.
对我来说 这是字面意义上的 我把圣经中的话当真 无论你们两个在哪里 我就在那里 我在那里 （译注：《马太福音》28章20节 “我常与你们同在 直到这世界的末了 ”）
It means the gift of freedom.
这意味着自由的礼物
It means God doesn't want to play that up there guarantee.
这意味着上帝不想在那上面保证一切
It means God entrusts the faith of creation, his own faith into us.
这意味着上帝将所创造的信仰 即他自己的信仰托付给我们
It means what happens here is part, as it were, of the history of God.
这意味着这里发生的事情可以说是上帝历史的一部分
although I don't agree with Amalo and Levinas.
虽然我不同意阿马洛和列维纳斯的观点
He made nicely this point.
他很好地阐述了这一点
Here, I agree with him, apropos iconoclasm.
在这里 我同意他的观点 即反传统观念
Don't misread it.
不要误解它
The prohibition to make image of God in Judaism
犹太教禁止制作上帝的形象
does not mean, oh, in this gnostic way, oh, it's too mysterious.
并不意味着 哦 以这种诺斯底方式 哦 它太神秘了
We cannot paint it.
我们不能描绘它
It means exact opposite.
它意味着完全相反
It means God is alive, not in your stupid deep meditations of up there, but how you react with others.
这意味着上帝活着 不是在你愚蠢的深层冥想中 而是在你如何与他人互动中
That's why you shouldn't make images, Because it's not an image to be made up there.
这就是为什么你不应该制作形象 因为它不是在那里可以制作出的形象
And I think, if anything even more, this holds for Christianity.
我认为 如果有什么更进一步的话 这也适用于基督教
That's for me what holy ghost is.
对我来说这就是圣灵
God is no longer the substantial master up there.
上帝不再是那个在上面的实质性主宰
God is, to put it in this way, the spirit of our community.
上帝 用这种方式说 是我们共享的精神
It's the gift of freedom.
它是自由的礼物
I claim, if you don't draw this crazy conclusion,
我认为 如果你不得出这个疯狂的结论
Then, whatever you claim to be, you repaganize Christianity.
那么 无论你声称自己是什么 你都是在使基督教重新异教化
You fall back at that level of God is up there sending messengers or whatever.
你回到了那个阶段 上帝在那上面派遣使者或其他什么
Sorry, but to inform you, although you know this, but Christ is not a messenger of God.
很抱歉 但要告诉你 虽然你知道这一点 但基督不是上帝的使者
Christ is God.
基督是上帝
I'm just trying to draw conclusions from what this means.
我只是试图从这意味着什么中得出结论
I'm sorry if I was too long.
很抱歉我讲得太长了
On the other hand, I'm not sorry.
另一方面 我并不抱歉
You had to suffer it.
你不得不忍受它
That's life.
那就是生活
Thanks very much.
非常感谢
And we have some time for questions, and what we thought we'd do so that everyone can hear
我们还有一些时间提问 我们想做的是让每个人都能听到
is we have a couple of microphones here and here, and so if you have a question pertaining to what was discussed and presented, you can cue up to the mic.
我们这里和这里有几个麦克风 所以如果你有关于讨论和展示的内容的问题 你可以排队到麦克风前
If you...
如果你...
Zizek said we should be a little bit liberal and allow those who would like to end their suffering to leave now, so...
齐泽克说我们应该有点自由主义 允许那些想要结束他们的痛苦的人现在就离开 所以...
Yeah, liberal, but did you see?
是的 自由 但你看到了吗
Goldfinger claims gold.
金手指声称黄金 （译注：电影《007：金手指》（Goldfinger） 其中"Goldfinger claims gold" 意思是 "Goldfinger 声称黄金" 指的是电影中的主要反派角色 Goldfinger 对黄金的迷恋和控制）
You remember that car where you press the button, no?
你还记得那辆车 你按下按钮 不是吗 （译注：指的是电影中的一辆特殊汽车 可能是指 007 曾经使用的具有特殊功能的汽车 其中可以通过按下按钮实现特殊的操作或功能 ）
My dream is to have here this kind of a plan.
我的梦想是在这里有这样的一个计划
You ask me a nasty question, I press the button, you jump up, and nonetheless.
你问我一个恶心的问题 我按下按钮 把你弹起来
Well, since we don't have that button, or maybe we do, I don't know.
既然我们没有那个按钮 或许我们有 我不知道
So if you feel like you'd like to leave, feel free.
所以如果你想离开 请随意
Otherwise, go ahead and we'll try to negotiate back and forth between the two.
否则 向前 我们会尝试在两者之间来回协调
Do you want to do or should I?
你想做还是我来做
There is a guy there already.
那边已经有个人了
Are we ready?
我们准备好了吗
Oh, OK.
哦 好的
So if you will comment briefly maybe on the connection between what you were talking about earlier and some of your other work in your writings.
那么 你能简要评论一下你之前谈论的内容与你其他作品和著作之间的联系吗
Maybe something about how in films like Independence Day where we saw the events that would later happen
也许是关于在《独立日》这样的电影中 我们看到了后来会发生的事件
and then we look at movies like the two you mentioned today where we didn't see what we knew happened.
然后我们看看今天你提到的两部电影 我们没有看到我们所知道的发生了的事情
Sorry, which is the second film, I didn't get it.
对不起 第二部电影是什么 我没听清
The two you discussed earlier, the two, the flight and the relationship between
之前你们讨论过的那两个 一个是关于飞行和关系的（译注：911）
the desert storm conflict where we watched the film or the war on television as if it were a film or we were experiencing it,
另一个是关于沙漠风暴冲突的（译注：海湾战争） 我们像看电影一样在电视上观看战争 或者我们正在经历它
and the current conflict where we dismiss it with media and just kind of talk about it from the point of view of DC.
还有当前的冲突 我们只是通过媒体将其消解 并且从华盛顿的角度来谈论它
There are so many, again, I will be short because it's, I hate you, because it's too good question in the sense to, you know what I mean?
有这么多 再次 我会很简短 因为这是一个太好的问题 以至于我恨你 你知道我的意思吗
To answer it properly, it's, again, half an hour and so on, no?
要恰当回答它 又是半小时 不是吗
What I want to say is that, first, when you said like Independence Day, we saw what happens later, no?
我想说的是 首先 当你说像《独立日》这样 我们看到了后来发生的事情 不是吗
My god, many people accused me when I wrote about this in my welcome.
天啊 当我在欢迎词中写到这一点时 很多人指责我
As if I'm some kind of a mean, evil, anti-American and wants to say, you see, you were dreaming about it.
好像我是某种卑鄙、邪恶、反美的人 想要说 你看 你梦想着它
So you basically got what you not only deserved, but desired.
所以你基本上不仅得到了你应得的 而且得到了你想要的
Here, things are much more complex.
在这里 事情要复杂得多
Because the first lesson of psychoanalysis is that it's also, I think, the title of that last novel of Truman Capote, Unfinished, something along these lines.
因为精神分析的第一课是 我认为 这也是杜鲁门·卡波特最后一部未完成小说的标题 大致是这样的
The worst thing that can happen to you is that your dreams come true, how should I put it?
最糟糕的事情是你的梦想成真 我该怎么说呢
The Freudian notion of desire is much more complex.
弗洛伊德关于欲望的概念要复杂得多
If you fantasize about something,
如果你对某件事有幻想
It is often that the worst thing that can happen is if this fantasy is brutally from outside imposed onto you.
通常最糟糕的事情是 如果这个幻想被外部粗暴地强加给你
In one of my books, I even make a very unpleasant.
在我的一本书中 我甚至用了一个非常不愉快的例子
I take a brutal example, but talking with many feminists who first were shocked, but then half accepted it, I'm convinced in the truth.
我引用了一个残酷的例子 但与许多最初感到震惊然后半接受它的女权主义者交谈后 我相信这个例子的真实性
Namely, you know, now this will be problematic for some of you, but at least listen to the end.
即 你知道 现在这可能对你们中的一些人来说是个问题 但至少听到最后
Do you remember this usual phrase of a rapist?
你还记得强奸犯的那句常用语吗
Oh, but she secretly deserved it.
哦 但她秘密地应得其罪
I only gave the bitch what she really was asking for.
我只是给了那个婊子她真正所求的
No, the standard defense is, oh, male fantasy, they dream about it, and so on.
不 标准的辩护是 哦 这是男性的幻想 他们梦想着它 等等
But when they speak frankly, many women will tell you.
但当他们坦率地说时 许多女性会告诉你
I read many minutes of reports on rape that it is true that there was some kind of desire.
我阅读了许多关于强奸的报告 确实存在某种欲望
Now comes my conclusion.
现在是我的结论
Does this justify it?
这就是它的合理化吗
Not.
不是
It's even more horrible.
这甚至更可怕
What do I mean by this?
我的意思是什么
I read in my country some reports on rape, and one thing is clear.
我在我的国家阅读了一些关于强奸的报告 有一件事是清楚的
I do it in one of my early books.
我在我的早期书籍中做了这件事
Imagine this situation, just to get the point.
想象这种情况 只是为了抓住要点
Of course, it's not as simple as that, but the basic point is like this.
当然 事情并不像那么简单 但基本要点是这样的
Imagine two women, to simplify to the utmost.
想象两个女人 为了极端简化
One is self-assertive, autonomous.
一个是自信的、自主的
The other is more passive, dreams about being beaten, raped, and so on.
另一个更被动 梦想着被殴打、强奸等等
Imagine both of them raped.
想象他们俩都被强奸了
I claim for the second one, it would have been much more terrifying.
我认为 对第二个人来说 这将是更加恐怖的
The first one will get over, maybe, I hope so, take even some revenge afterwards.
第一个人可能会克服 我希望如此 之后甚至可能会报复
For the second one, who?
对于第二个人来说 谁
At a certain level, you can say, oh, she just got what she was dreaming about.
在某种程度上 你可以说 哦 她只是得到了她一直梦想的东西
For that one, I fear she may kill herself, and so on,
对那个人来说 我担心她可能会自杀等
I claim afterwards.
我认为 也就是说 没有什么比从外部像被扇在你脸上一样得到你梦想的事实更屈辱的了
Because you know, fantasies are a very fragile thing.
因为你知道 幻想是一种非常脆弱的东西
So back to that point, I think this is a different question, but very interesting one.
所以回到那个观点 我认为这是一个不同的问题 但非常有趣
Why this eternal fascination of the United States with the victory of the enemy from all those fantasies.
为什么美国总是在这些幻想中 对敌人的胜利充满着永恒的迷恋
And I like them, all those stories where there was, I think, with, I don't know who played in it, a big miniseries some 10, 20 years ago
我喜欢它们 所有那些故事 我认为 我不知道是谁参与了 大概10、20年前的一部大型迷你剧
where Soviet Union occupied the United States, and then daily life.
苏联占领了美国 然后是日常生活
And even the last one, I bought it, my god, at the airport now four days ago.
甚至是最后一个 我在机场买的 我的天 就在四天前
I forgot some Italian sounding author, prayers for the assassins.
我忘了一些听起来像意大利人的作者 为凶手祈祷
The idea is atomic bombs, blah, blah, blah, war.
故事是原子弹 等等 战争
The result, United States falls apart.
结果 美国分崩离析
Southeast, Bible Belt Republic, New York, that area, atomic waste, and LA, Northwest in Seattle, Islamic Republic of the United States.
东南部 圣经地带共和国 纽约 那个地区 是原子废墟 而洛杉矶 西北部的西雅图 美国的伊斯兰共和国
And it's a very nice novel because it doesn't paint Islam simply as bad.
这是一本非常好的小说 因为它没有简单地将伊斯兰描绘为坏的
It tries to imagine how it would have felt.
它试图想象它会是什么感觉
But again, the point is, what ideological pleasure do you get from it, no?
但再次 重点是 你从中获得什么意识形态上的快感 不是吗
So, OK, I would have to go on too much.
所以 好吧 我本可以继续下去
But to go your other points about where we get, we didn't see, and so on, and so on, I'm not, no,
但回到你的其他点上 关于我们没有看到的 等等 我不是 不
I will make another point here.
我将在这里提出另一个观点
And that's all I can say now.
这就是我现在能说的全部
I am not saying, maybe I gave a wrong impression, that the true film would have been the one which would have provided a total picture with all historical causes of the events, no, I already hinted a couple of versions of what would have been a more truthful film.
我不是说 也许我给了错误的印象 真正的电影会是那种提供了所有历史原因的完整画面的电影 不 我已经暗示了几个版本 什么样的电影会更真实
For example, as I said, American 11 instead of United 93.
例如 正如我所说的 《美国航班11》而不是《联合93》
That is to say, not some kind of Marxist, optimistic, total knowledge, but at least the true despair, how should I put it, no?
也就是说 不是某种马克思主义的、乐观的、全部的知识 但至少是真正的绝望 我该怎么说
At least the true despair.
至少是真正的绝望
And again, this doesn't involve any kind of secret pseudo-leftist justification.
再说一遍 这并不涉及对任何秘密的伪左派辩护
ha ha, you got what you want, or whatever.
哈哈 你得到了你想要的 或者什么的
No, it's just, how should I put it, the problem is simply precisely to confront things in all their horror.
不 它只是 问题简单地确切地在于面对所有的恐怖
What bothers me in this aggressive, either here Republican attitude, it's a feature which somehow strangely, this idea that you can only tell the story when people fight back.
这种咄咄逼人的态度让我感到困扰 无论是共和党的态度 还是一种奇怪的特征 即只有当人们反击时你才能讲述故事
And you know that this was the same in communist countries.
你知道 这在共产主义国家也是一样的
It's a strange thing why, when they were dealing with those who survived the concentration camps, the communist regimes always found it a kind of irrational hatred and guilt.
奇怪的是 为什么共产党政权在对待那些集中营幸存者的时候 总是会有一种非理性的仇恨和愧疚
Usually, all those Russian soldiers who were freed from Nazi camps, most of them were sent to Siberia killed.
通常 所有那些从纳粹营地释放的俄罗斯士兵 大多数都被送往西伯利亚被杀
or even worse, in my country, Slovenia, part of x-Yugoslavia, we avoided Stalinist show trials.
或者更糟 在我的国家 斯洛文尼亚 前南斯拉夫的一部分 我们避免了斯大林式的示范审判
But there was one show trial monstrous in 51.
但在51年有一次可怕的示范审判
It was called Dachau trial.
它被称为达豪审判
The survivors of Dachau were put to trial, accused of surviving Dachau because they collaborated with the Germans.
达豪的幸存者被审判 被指控因为与德国人合作而幸存下来
And then there are no English spies, the usual story.
然后他们是英国间谍 通常的故事
But what fascinated, I think, what is beneath is that the communists couldn't imagine this true despair,
但吸引人的是 我认为 共产党人无法想象这种真正的绝望
that there are situations where you can be so humiliated that it's no longer possible this heroic stance, shoot, but I fight back, and so on, no?
有些情况下你可以被羞辱到不再可能采取这种英雄式的立场 射击 但我反击 等等 不是吗
They still, it's somehow too embarrassing, unimaginable to them,
他们仍然觉得 这种绝望太尴尬、难以想象
this utter despair embodied in the figure of this nicely described in Agamben's book about Auschwitz, these Muslims, Muslim men, and this living dead, totally broken.
这种彻底的绝望体现在阿甘本关于奥斯威辛集中营的著作中 这些穆斯林、穆斯林男子和这个活死人的形象中 他们完全崩溃了
Or to put it in another way, it's a very sensitive topic, but I insist on it.
或者换一种方式说 这是一个非常敏感的话题 但我坚持它
Did you notice a strange fact that most of the really good films about Holocaust and so on are comedies?
你有没有注意到一个奇怪的事实 大多数关于大屠杀等的真正好电影都是喜剧
I think there is a deeper necessity in it.
我认为这其中有更深的必然性
What kind of necessity?
什么样的必然性
Tragedy can only be written.
悲剧只能被写出来
something can be staged, presented as tragedy, when things are not really, truly desperate to the end.
当事情并非真正、真正绝望到最后时 某些事情可能会被上演 呈现为悲剧
Because in tragedy, you retain a minimum of dignity to play your tragic role with this heroic dignity.
因为在悲剧中 你保留了一点尊严 以这种英雄式的尊严扮演你的悲剧角色
So a film which would have taken place, for example, in Auschwitz as a tragedy would have been an obscenity, I claim.
所以 如果有一部电影发生在奥斯威辛 作为一部悲剧 我认为那将是一种亵渎
It would have given too much credit to the Nazis.
这会给纳粹太多的功劳
The whole point is that the terror was so total that it was not possible to do a conflict at the level of tragedy, which is why some of the scenes, if you read Primo Levi, the way he described,
重点是 恐怖是如此全面 以至于不可能在悲剧的层面上进行冲突 这就是为什么如果你读普里莫·莱维的描述 有些场景 你只能将它们描述为滑稽的
For example, one of the most horrible scenes, read it in, if this is a man when every two months you had in Auschwitz camp a process called selection.
例如 最可怕的场景之一 在《如果这是一个人》中读到 奥斯威辛营地每两个月进行一次所谓的选择过程
All prisoners have to run naked in front of a SS doctor.
所有囚犯必须赤裸着在一名医生面前跑过
And the doctor was tired, didn't care.
医生累了 不在乎
Literally, you had two, three seconds to impress the doctor, that you are healthy enough to survive.
字面上 你有两三秒钟的时间给医生留下印象 证明你健康到足以生存
And he simply categorize you to be burned or to allowed to live.
他简单地将你分类 是被烧死还是被允许活下来
But there is something obscenely, madly comical in this, how Primo Levi describes this.
但普里莫·莱维如何描述这一切中有一种亵渎、疯狂的滑稽感
You know, like the prisoners were trying to pinch their lips to appear more healthy, more red, their stomachs tried to rise.
你知道 就像囚犯们试图捏紧嘴唇以显得更健康、更红一样 他们的胃也试图起伏
It's kind of a totally crazy comedy, no dignity in it.
这是一种完全疯狂的喜剧 没有尊严
And that's the true horror of it, I claim.
我认为 这就是它的真正恐怖所在
So the same goes for Stalinist show trials, and so on, and so on.
所以 斯大林式的示范审判等等也是如此
When in this sense, I claim, and Kierkegaard knew this, Christianity is a comedy.
在这个意义上 我声称 而且克尔凯郭尔知道这一点 基督教是一种喜剧
Christianity, to read crucifixion as a tragedy is an obscenity.
把基督教的十字架看作悲剧是种亵渎
Tragedy is for ancient Greeks.
悲剧是给古希腊人的
For the Christian, it's comedy.
对基督徒来说 这是喜剧
But of course, the whole point being comedy, which is much more nightmarish than more.
但当然 重点是喜剧 这比更多的噩梦更可怕
So again, I didn't answer your question.
所以再次 我没有回答你的问题
I know, but there was too much in it.
我知道 但里面内容太多了
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
I cannot go in there.
我不能深入讨论
Ah, sorry.
啊 抱歉
Please.
请
Thank you.
谢谢
At the end of your talk, he said that Jesus, by God through Jesus, gives us the gift of freedom, and that is Christianity as you read it.
在你的演讲结束时 他说耶稣 上帝通过耶稣 给了我们自由的礼物 这就是你读到的基督教
That really made me think about an earlier statement you made about the idea of, for example, the paradoxical statements you were making about we have freedom to choose as long as we don't choose it.
这确实让我想起了您之前所做的关于这个想法的陈述 例如 您所做的关于 只要我们不选择 我们就有选择的自由 这个矛盾的陈述
So on some level, can you reconcile that with Calvinism?
在某种层面上 你能将其与加尔文主义调和吗
Since we're here at Calvin College, I'm just wondering, are you an atheist Calvinist on some level?
既然我们在加尔文学院 我就想知道 你在某种层面上是不是一个无神论的加尔文主义者
No, if you, okay.
不 如果你 好吧
Paradoxically.
矛盾地
Almost.
几乎
If you ask me which religious orientation would be of Christianity, would be closest
如果你问我哪个宗教取向是基督教 最接近我的自发敏感度
to my spontaneous sensitivity, generally Protestantism, but maybe those who are closer to Protestants among Catholics, Pascal, Poirot, why?
通常是新教 但也许是那些与天主教徒更接近的新教徒 像帕斯卡尔 波伊洛 为什么
Because we can debate about everything.
因为我们可以讨论一切
One thing I don't concede, this obscenity that our salvation depends on our good acts.
我不会让步的一件事是 这种亵渎观念 即我们的救赎取决于我们的善行
I think this is an obscenity for me, an obscenity in the sense that this then introduces an irreducible aspect of, you know, as if, oh God, okay, if I make this, will it be okay that of kind of economic exchange or whatever.
我认为这对我来说是种亵渎 意味着引入了一种不可减少的方面 就好像 哦 上帝 好吧 如果我做这个 会不会没问题 那种经济交换或其他什么的
It has to be predestination.
这必须是宿命论
That's where I totally agree with it.
在这一点上 我完全同意
And now comes the point, oh my God, I hate you, why are you asking me two good questions?
现在来到了这一点 哦 我的天 我恨你 为什么你要问我两个好问题
Have you thought about this paradox, I've written about it, which is a crazy paradox,
你有没有想过这个悖论 我已经写过它了 这是一个疯狂的悖论
namely how we all know Max Weber, capitalism, Protestantism, but if we approach it with a common sense, it would have been that capitalism, as we know, the most dynamic, competitive system in the history of humanity.
即我们都知道马克斯·韦伯 资本主义 新教 但如果我们用常识来接近它 本应该是资本主义 正如我们所知 是人类历史上最动态、最有竞争力的系统
You are up to you, you are autonomous, you work like crazy.
你由你自己决定 你是自主的 你疯狂地工作
How is it that this attitude is justified by the notion of predestination, which, if
宿命论的观念是如何证明这种态度的合理性的
you approach it in a common sense way, should have justified precisely the opposite attitude, to be vulgar if everything is decided in advance?
如果你用常识方式接近它 本应该恰恰证明相反的态度 用通俗的话说 如果一切都是提前决定的
Why don't I sit down, read pornography, and drink lemonade?
为什么我不坐下来 看色情材料 喝柠檬水呢
You know, like, why were everything is already decided?
你知道 像 为什么一切都已经决定了
So it's mysterious.
所以这是神秘的
How is it that precisely the awareness that everything is decided in advance pushes us to incessant activity?
为什么正是意识到一切都是提前决定的 却推动我们不断地活动
My answer would be here problematic for some theologists maybe, but I'm convinced by it.
我的回答在这里对某些神学家来说可能是有问题的 但我相信它
that predestination is an extremely refined dialectical notion.
宿命论是一个极其精炼的辩证概念
It's not simply it's written up there.
它不仅仅是已经写好的
It's that it's written up there, but you don't know what is written, no?
它是已经写好的 但你不知道写的是什么 不是吗
And I think that we should make clear here a step further that even say it is written up there, but it is backwards written.
我认为我们应该在这里进一步明确 甚至说它是已经写好的 但它是倒写的
What do I mean by this?
我的意思是什么
There is a very refined paradox which theorists of even some theorists of rational action articulated, of how something may happen or not.
这是一个非常精炼的悖论 甚至一些理性行动的理论家也表达了 关于某事可能发生或不发生
But if it happens, retroactively it appears that it had to happen from the beginning.
但如果它发生了 事后看来它从一开始就必须发生
For example, all good histories of the Roman Civil War, Julius Caesar, and so on, will tell you how once Caesar won, everybody saw it as a destiny, no?
例如 所有关于罗马内战的好历史 朱利叶斯·凯撒等 都会告诉你 一旦凯撒赢了 每个人都视之为命中注定 不是吗
But it is as if things are not necessary from the beginning.
但就好像事情从一开始就不是必然的
So that the paradox is that if a thing happens, you have to say retroactively that it had to happen.
所以悖论是 如果某事发生了 你必须在事后说它必须发生
Retroactively.
事后
And this brings me to another.
这让我想到了另一个
I love, as a Marxist, I love religious conservatives.
作为一个马克思主义者 我喜欢宗教保守主义者
You find intelligent conservatives.
你会发现聪明的保守主义者
Like TS Eliot, you know that, my god, if you study English, the most traditional and individual talent.
比如T.S.艾略特 你知道 我的天 如果你学英语 最传统和个人才华
That famous phrase, the proposition how every great work of art retroactively changes its entire past.
那句著名的话 关于每一部伟大的艺术作品如何反过来改变其整个过去
Or it's the same Borges said something similar in his wonderful text on Kafka, that a modest writer, you can say by whom he or she was influenced, a truly great writer,
或者是博尔赫斯在他关于卡夫卡的精彩文本中说的类似的话 一个普通的作家 你可以说他或她受到了谁的影响 一个真正伟大的作家
creates its own, his or her own precursors.
创造了他或她自己的先驱
His idea is that, of course, we can say Kafka was influenced by Dostoevsky, Edgar Lampeau,
他的想法是 当然 我们可以说卡夫卡受到了陀思妥耶夫斯基、埃德加·爱伦坡、
William Blake, whatever.
威廉·布莱克等的影响
But it's not as simple as that.
但情况并非如此简单
But to perceive that dimension in Dostoevsky, blah, blah, blah, Kafka already had to be here.
但要感知到陀思妥耶夫斯基等人那样的维度 卡夫卡已经必须在这里了
Now, this doesn't mean we simply retroactively project it.
现在 这并不意味着我们简单地反向投射它
I think that this retroactive constitution of necessity is the key to predestination.
我认为这种对必然性的反向构建是宿命论的关键
Predestination doesn't mean we are not free.
宿命论并不意味着我们不自由
Predestination means that we are, at the much more radical level, free to constitute our very predestination, how should I put it?
宿命论意味着我们在更根本的层面上自由 自由地构建我们自己的宿命 我该怎么说呢
Because that's the paradox of freedom.
因为那是自由的悖论
Freedom, here I agree with deepest insights of Protestants.
在这里 我同意新教最深刻的洞见
True freedom is not, oh, do I want a strawberry cake or a chocolate cake or whatever, this and that.
真正的自由不是 哦 我想要草莓蛋糕还是巧克力蛋糕 或者其他这个那个
True freedom is in a way to choose your necessity, how should I put it, no?
真正的自由在某种程度上是选择你的必然性 我该怎么说呢 不是吗
True freedom is something much more difficult.
真正的自由是一种更加困难的东西
For example, let's take the ultimate free act, love.
例如 让我们以最终的自由行为为例 爱
Of course, love has to be free.
当然 爱必须是自由的
If somebody tells me you have to love this, that, it doesn't work.
如果有人告诉我你必须爱这个那个 它就不起作用
But it's a strange kind of freedom because at the same time, let me be extremely vulgar.
但这是一种奇怪的自由 因为同时 让我非常粗俗地说
You notice that I like to be, I use the, it's nice to be hypocritical and put the blame.
你注意到我喜欢这样 我用这个 假装虚伪并推卸责任是很好的
You know, I really don't want to be vulgar but for the sake of argument, sake of argument.
你知道 我真的不想粗俗 但为了争论起见 为了争论起见
Okay.
好的
Let's say if I were to say here are some nice girls, let me fall in love and I look around.
比方说 如果我要在这里说有些漂亮的女孩 让我坠入爱河 我四处看看
Ah, you have nice hair, my legs like that.
啊 你的头发很漂亮 我喜欢那样的腿
OK, the most percentage, it's you.
好吧 最有可能的是你
No, I will not point at anyone, not to be accused of harassment.
不 我不会指向任何人 以免被控骚扰
And it doesn't work, isn't it?
这不行 不是吗
The whole point of love is that it is free,
爱的全部要点是它是自由的
the freest maybe act of all.
也许是所有行为中最自由的
But what kind of, how do you experience it?
但这种 你是如何体验它的
All of a sudden, you experience it as I cannot do otherwise but that.
突然间 你体验到的是我除此之外无法做其他
That's my necessity.
那是我的必然性
I have to do it.
我必须这么做
And it's the same with all great acts of freedom, not through chocolate cake or strawberry cake.
所有伟大的自由行为都是一样的 不是通过选择巧克力蛋糕或草莓蛋糕
But for example, you are in a difficult predicament.
但例如 你处于一个困难的境地
There is war, or let's say in Europe, Nazi occupation, whatever, to decide to fight it, to engage in fight.
有战争 或者比如在欧洲 纳粹占领 无论什么 决定反抗 参与战斗
It's probably the utmost free decision.
这可能是最终的自由决定
But it's not that when you decide for it in a way, or for example, for a white man here in the 50s
但这不是当你为之决定的方式 或者例如 对于50年代这里的白人男性
to really do it, not as a white liberal signing protests up there in New York, but like those white men who were killed here, to come really not here, we are up down there in the south.
真正地去做 而不是像在纽约那些白人自由派签署抗议书那样 而是像那些在这里被杀的白人男性 真正来到这里 在南方
Sorry, I still think, I thought that I was where I was two days ago in the south.
对不起 我仍然以为 我以为我两天前还在南方
To go really down there and risk to be killed supporting the blacks and so on.
真正去那里冒着被杀的风险来支持黑人等等
It's obscene to say, oh, I was free to decide, I decided.
说“哦 我自由地做出了决定 我决定了 ”是可憎的
You decided because in some way you sense that you would be ashamed of yourself, you cannot do otherwise.
你之所以做出决定 是因为在某种程度上你感觉到你会为自己感到羞耻 你别无选择
This is the deepest sense, not this neurological sense, when you think you are free, you are controlled by your neurons.
这是最深刻的意义 不是那种神经学的意义 当你认为你是自由的 你却受你的神经元控制
This is the deepest sense in which the highest freedom is assuming inner necessity.
这是最深层的意义 最高的自由就是承担内在的必然性
So I know, again, that I didn't answer you, but here you see how I relate very intensely to all this topic of predestination and so on.
所以我知道 我又没回答你的问题 但你看我是如何非常激烈地关联到所有这些关于宿命论等主题的
And definitely, definitely, I think that all the, how to put it, I even, now I'm writing a book on Hegel and Christianity, where I try to develop this, my god, I will be hated for that again, was this political, how very Eurocentric, unashamed, and pro-Protestant.
而且绝对 我认为所有这些 怎么说 我甚至正在写一本关于黑格尔和基督教的书 在那里我试图发展这个 我的天 我又会因此被讨厌 是这个政治 非常欧洲中心主义 毫不掩饰 亲新教
First, we have Eastern Orthodoxy,
首先 我们有东正教
which for me is, I mean, as Christianity, I mean, Russian church, that orthodoxy, not John Milbank, not here, radical orthodoxy, neither East Buddhism, but that one.
对我来说 是 我的意思是 作为基督教 我的意思是 俄罗斯教会 那个东正教 不是约翰·米尔班克这里的激进正统 也不是东方佛教 而是那一个
I'm very uneasy with that one.
我对那个非常不安
Because first, this whole, I think they secretly change Christ into kind of an idol, a mere ideal to be imitated.
因为首先 我认为他们秘密地将基督变成了一种偶像 一个仅仅被模仿的理想
And then in the long term, we all can become Christ.
然后从长远来看 我们都可以成为基督
You know, this idea of man becoming God, gradually we will all becoming God,
你知道 这种人逐渐成为上帝的想法 我们最终都将成为上帝
connected with another problem which I find very problematic in Orthodox Christian church.
与我发现在东正教基督教会中非常有问题的另一个问题相关
The notion of this distinction between what they call economy and God in itself, as if you can distinguish in God the inner mystery, trinity, of God himself and economy, which is basically to be cynical public relations, how God deals with humanity.
他们所谓的经济和上帝本身之间的这种区别的概念 就好像你可以在上帝中区分上帝本身和经济的内在神秘 三位一体 这基本上是愤世嫉俗的公共关系 上帝如何对待人类
But I think that what gets lost here is simply the deepest Christian insight, which you find in,
但我认为这里丢失的是基督教最深刻的洞察 你只能在最纯粹的新教以及可能的一些神秘主义者那里找到 比如迈斯特·艾克哈特 他明白了什么是最深刻的洞察
it's that we are part of God's history, how should I put it?
那就是我们是上帝历史的一部分 我该怎么说
It's not God up there.
不是上帝在天上
So I claim that Catholicism, you have more this symbolic exchange.
所以我声称天主教 你有更多这种象征性交换
You deal with God, institution, and so on.
你与上帝、制度等打交道
I quite naively believe, so here I'm totally for it, that only with Protestantism did
我相当天真地相信 所以在这里我完全支持 只有通过新教
Christianity, again, to use this nice Hegelian dialectical formulation, only with Protestantism Did Christianity become what it always truly was, as I put it?
基督教再次 使用这个漂亮的黑格尔辩证法公式 只有通过新教 基督教才成为了它本来真正的样子 我是这么说的
Here again, you have this nice paradox, which is properly Christian Hegelian dialectical paradox, that there is eternity.
这里再次 你有这个漂亮的悖论 这是纯粹的基督教黑格尔辩证法悖论 即存在永恒
But eternity is something which can become through time.
但永恒是可以通过时间而成的东西
Not simply that it wasn't there, it becomes what it always already was.
不仅仅是它不存在 而是它变成了它始终所是的样子
OK, I'm sorry if I was wrong.
好吧 如果我说错了我很抱歉
Again, these are serious problems.
再次 这些都是严肃的问题
If you come again, you can tell us what toilets are like in Slovenia.
如果你再来 你可以告诉我们斯洛文尼亚的厕所是怎样的
Thank you.
谢谢
Germans, we are disgusting Germans.
德国人 我们是恶心的德国人
That was a joke.
那是个玩笑
Next person.
下一个问题
We are disgusting Germans.
我们是恶心的德国人
Sorry to inform you.
很抱歉告诉你
I've got a very simple question for you.
我有一个非常简单的问题要问你
Oh my god, this will be the really nasty one.
哦 天哪 这将是真正讨厌的问题
You already got asked the question about Calvinism.
你已经被问到了关于加尔文主义的问题
But going back to your presentation and the scope of human suffering and how that all kind of fits or it doesn't fit with Christianity.
但回到你的演讲和人类苦难的范围以及这些如何适应或不适应基督教的话题
To me, kind of, you stopped at crucifixion.
对我来说 你好像在十字架上就停下来了
And I find it kind of narrowing to talk about Christian tradition at large without the resurrection, how resurrection fits into what you just said or how it doesn't fit.
我发现在没有复活的情况下谈论整个基督教传统有点狭隘 复活是否适合你刚才所说的
It does.
它适合
But here, maybe I'm a little bit too much in favor of some kind of materialist rereading, no?
但在这里 也许我有点过于偏爱某种唯物主义的重新解读 不是吗
I mean, resurrection is, for me, what I quoted, that when the two of you will be there and love between you, I will be there.
我的意思是 对我来说 复活就是我引用的 当你们两个在那里并且你们之间有爱时 我也会在那里
Resurrection, for me, is the Holy Ghost.
对我来说 复活是圣灵
You don't need any Christ to meddle things up there, Hersey.
你不需要任何基督在那里搅乱事情 异端
OK, so your definition of Christian Protestantism will be more of the 19th century liberal tradition.
那么 你对基督教新教的定义将更多属于19世纪的自由主义传统
Oh my god, no.
哦 我的天 不
If we were to be, sorry to tell you this, But if we were to be in Soviet Union in the 30s,
如果我们要在30年代的苏联
even before you would reach home, you would disappear in a camp of re-education, five years minimum.
甚至在你到家之前 你就会消失在一个至少五年的再教育营中
No, seriously, because no, my god, I'm Kierkegaardian here.
不 说真的 因为不 我的天 我在这里是克尔凯郭尔式的
And the greatness of Kierkegaard is that people usually misread Kierkegaard because they misread him as if his point was no, not institution, but inner faith, absolutely not.
克尔凯郭尔的伟大之处在于人们通常误读他 因为他们误解了他 好像他的观点不是制度 而是内在的信仰 绝对不是
Kierkegaard is, this is for me, the miracle of Kierkegaard.
克尔凯郭尔 这对我来说 是克尔凯郭尔的奇迹
He knew very well in his critique of what he called Christendom, the Christianity as institution, that the solution is not this liberal attitude of what it only truly matters is your inner faith.
他非常清楚地在他对所谓基督教国 即作为制度的基督教的批判中 解决方案不是这种自由主义态度 即只有你的内在信仰才是真正重要的
OK, let me give you a radical answer.
好吧 让我给你一个激进的回答
If I were to choose, OK, I'll do it this way.
如果我不得不选择 好吧 我会这样做
I have many friends who are this kind of half closet materialist closet believers, and they even don't know in which closet they really are or whatever.
我有很多这种半隐蔽的唯物主义者、隐蔽的信徒朋友 他们甚至不知道他们自己是不是潜在的信徒
I ask them, I like this brutal, do you believe or not?
我问他们 我喜欢这种残酷的问题 你相信吗
The usual answer I get is really not.
我通常得到的答案是真的不相信
I don't like institutions, but there is something deep in me, maybe some force, blah, blah, blah.
我不喜欢制度 但我的内心深处有些东西 也许是某种力量 等等
I have no mercy for this.
我对此毫不留情
To me, what is much more sympathetic, what interests me is precisely church as an institution.
对我来说 更令我同情的是 我对教会作为一个制度特别感兴趣
Church as an institution, which is why what interests me is Protestantism.
教会作为一个制度 这就是为什么我对新教特别感兴趣
It's not this, me and God.
这不是我和上帝之间的事
No, it's Gemeinde, it's the community.
不 这是Gemeinde（译注：德语 社区） 是社区
That's absolutely crucial for me, which is why, for example, I totally agree with that basic Protestant insight.
这对我来说绝对至关重要 这就是为什么 例如 我完全同意那个基本的新教洞察
What does it mean, read Bible alone?
独自阅读圣经是什么意思
It doesn't mean kind of inner orgasm of meditation, blah, blah.
这并不意味着某种内在的冥想高潮 等等
It means God's work for me.
这意味着上帝对我而言的作用
Read Bible means precisely
阅读圣经确切地意味着你不能绕过逻各斯（Logos）
This is even the limitation for me of all those mystics.
这甚至是我对所有那些神秘主义者的限制
Like, great as he is, but Meister Eckhart cannot really deal with incarnation, with Christ.
比如 伟大的迈斯特·艾克哈特 他真的无法处理化身成肉身、处理基督
Did you notice how the whole operation of Meister Eckhart, his mystical rereading of Christianity, is based on this basically treating with works?
你注意到了吗 迈斯特·艾克哈特的整个操作 他对基督教的神秘主义重新解读 基本上是基于这种对作品的处理吗
I think you have been letting this ambiguity mundus, now it can means pure and world.
我认为你一直让这种模糊不清的"mundus"（译注：拉丁语 世界）存在 现在它可以指纯净和世界
So here it is, God sends his son into mundus whatever, not as into the world, but into the purity of our virgin soul.
所以在这里 上帝把他的儿子送入了'无论何等的mundus' 不是送入世界 而是送入我们纯洁的灵魂中
I think you lose everything in this way.
我认为这样你就失去了一切
But going back so that I don't get lost, to your point, what I'm especially opposed to is this secular humanist notion of this Feuerbach version of you, it doesn't matter what you believe,
但回到你的观点 我特别反对的是这种世俗人文主义观念 这种费尔巴哈式的观点 你信什么不重要
Christianity is more a kind of an ideal, you know, it's really we just project into it our highest human desires, what is most noble in us, and so on and so on.
基督教更多是一种理想 你知道 这实际上是我们把我们最高尚的人类欲望投射进去 我们内在最高尚的东西 等等
No, I think it's absolutely crucial to insist, I cannot develop it now, that man is not enough to, you must have a dimension which is more radical than only a man in man,
不 我认为绝对重要的是坚持 我现在无法发展它 “人”还不够 你必须有一个比仅仅是人类更根本的维度
and I cannot go now into it theoretically, but even in psychoanalysis, I claim, this is the function of a concept which is deeply misunderstood, the concept of death drive.
我现在无法从理论上探讨这个问题 但即使在精神分析中 我声称 这是一个被深深误解的概念的功能 即死亡冲动的概念
Death drive is not this, oh, I want to die, disappear, or some kind of crazy destructive drive paradoxically, I claim is Freud's name for immortality.
死亡冲动并不是“哦 我想要死去、消失” 或者某种疯狂的破坏性驱动 我声称 这是弗洛伊德用来表示不朽的名字
If you really want to understand what is death drive, forgot about all this nirvana stuff and think about Stephen King.
如果你真的想了解什么是死亡冲动 忘掉所有这些涅槃的东西 想想斯蒂芬·金
You know what I mean?
你知道我是什么意思吗
This undead, in the sense of death, but living death.
这种不死之人 死亡的意义上的不死 却是一种活着的死亡
Something which insists beyond life and death.
某种超越生与死的坚持
So again, in this sense, sorry for my tastelessness, but you got my point, in this sense,
所以 再次 在这个意义上 抱歉我的低俗 但你明白我的意思 在这个意义上
No, I'm definitely opposed to this, how should I put it, this soft religious humanism.
不 我是绝对反对这个 怎么说呢 这种软弱的宗教人文主义
Who cares, institutionally, just that you are sincere and that whatever, no.
制度上谁在乎 只要你是真诚的 不管怎样
No, no, no, here I am a strict Kierkegaardian, who, again, what Kierkegaard got,
不 不 不 在这里我是一个严格的基督教哲学家 再次 基督教哲学家所明白的
and this was a great, almost, I would say, Marxist insight by him, is that wasn't, you know, better this than me, wasn't a big target of Kierkegaard's
这是他的一种伟大的 我几乎要说是马克思主义者的洞察
was some big state theologist, I forgot the name, who was precisely this kind of a liberal.
不是某种大国家神学家 我忘记了名字 恰好是这种自由主义者
And what Kierkegaard got is that there is no opposition between this kind of flat,
基督教哲学家所看到的是 这种肤浅、廉价的、感情用事的人道主义与成为最坏的顺从国家哲学家之间并不存在对立